<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="tei-analysis.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="chs-gp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>The Saint Chad Gospels</title>
				<editor xml:id="bh">Bonnie Lewis, Tucker Hannah</editor>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>A new transcription from digital imagery, with semantic markup, based on digital images captured by the University of Kentucky’s Center for Visualization and Virtual Environments, Brent Seales, Director. The images are copyrighted by the Chapter of Lichfield Cathedral, 2010, and are released under a Creative Commons License. This material is based upon work supported by the National Science Foundation under Grants No. 0916148 &amp; No. 0916421. Any opinions, findings and conclusions or recomendations expressed in this material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation (NSF).</edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
					<name>Tucker Hannah, Tony Brown, Christopher Blackwell, Brent Seales edd.</name>
					
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>under 1Mb</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher> The Center for Hellenic Studies of Harvard University </publisher>
				<authority>
					<name>Casey Dué and Mary Ebbott, edd.</name>
				</authority>
				<availability>
					<p>©2010, The Center for Hellenic Studies. This work is made available under the
						Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 United States
						License: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/us/</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>File created electronically.</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="eng">English</language>
				<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
				<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
				<language ident="xgrc">Transliterated Greek</language>
				<language ident="deu">German</language>
				<language ident="fra">French</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>	
	<text xml:lang="eng">
		<body>
			<div n="1" type="chapter">
				<p>
					<seg n="1" type="verse">The beginning of the good news about Jesus the Messiah, the Son of God
					    <seg type="pb" n="72r" /></seg>
					<seg n="2" type="verse">as it is written in Isaiah the prophet: <seg type="lb" n="1" /> I will
					    send my messenger ahead of you who will prepare <seg type="lb" n="2" /> your way</seg>
					<seg n="3" type="verse">a voice of one calling in the wilderness <seg type="lb" n="3" /> Prepare
					    the way for the Lord, make straight paths for him <seg type="lb" n="4" /></seg>
					<seg n="4" type="verse">And so John the Baptist appeared in the wilderness preaching
					    <seg type="lb" n="5" /> a baptism of repentance for the forgiveness <seg type="lb" n="6" /> of sins</seg>
					<seg n="5" type="verse">The whole Judean countryside and <seg type="lb" n="7" /> all the people
					    of Jerusalem went out to him. Confessing their sins, they were baptized <seg type="lb" n="8" />
					    by him in the Jordan River <seg type="lb" n="9" />.</seg>
					<seg n="6" type="verse">John wore clothing <seg type="lb" n="10" /> made of camel's hair, with a
					    leather belt around his waist <seg type="lb" n="11" />, and he ate locusts and wild honey.
					    <seg type="lb" n="12" /></seg>
					<seg n="7" type="verse">And this was his message: “After me <seg type="lb" n="13" /> comes the one
					    more powerful than I, <seg type="lb" n="14" /> the straps of whose sandals I am not worthy to stoop
					    down and untie.</seg>
					<seg n="8" type="verse">I baptize <seg type="lb" n="15" /> you with water, but he will baptize you
					     with the Holy Spirit.” <seg type="lb" n="16" /></seg>
				</p>
				<p>
					<seg n="9" type="verse">At that time Jesus came from Nazareth <seg type="lb" n="17" /> in Galilee
					    and was baptized by John in the Jordan. <seg type="lb" n="18" /></seg>
					<seg n="10" type="verse">Just as Jesus was coming up out of the water, he saw heaven being torn
					    <seg type="lb" n="19" /> open and the Spirit descending <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="72v" />
					    on him like a dove.</seg>
					<seg n="11" type="verse">And a voice came <seg type="lb" n="1" /> from heaven: “You are my Son,
					    whom I love <seg type="lb" n="2" /> with you I am well pleased.”</seg>
					<seg n="12" type="verse">At once the Spirit sent him out into the wilderness, <seg type="lb" n="3" /></seg>
					<seg n="13" type="verse">and he was in the wilderness forty days <seg type="lb" n="4" />,
					     being tempted by Satan. <seg type="lb" n="5" /> He was with the wild animals, and angels attended
					    <seg type="lb" n="6" /> him.</seg>
					<seg n="14" type="verse">After John was put in prison, <seg type="lb" n="7" /> Jesus went into
					    Galilee, proclaiming <seg type="lb" n="8" /> the good news of God.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="15" type="verse">“The time has come,” <seg type="lb" n="9" /> he said. “The kingdom of God
					     has come near. <seg type="lb" n="10" /> Repent and believe the good news!”</seg>
					<seg n="16" type="verse">As Jesus walked beside <seg type="lb" n="11" /> the Sea of Galilee, he saw
					    Simon and his brother Andrew <seg type="lb" n="12" /> casting a net into the lake, for they were
					    <seg type="lb" n="13" /> fishermen.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p>	
					<seg n="17" type="verse">“Come, follow me,” Jesus said,  <seg type="lb" n="14" /> “and I will send
					    you out to fish for people.” <seg type="lb" n="15" /></seg>
					<seg n="18" type="verse">At once they left their nets and followed him. <seg type="lb" n="16" /></seg>
					<seg n="19" type="verse">When he had gone a little farther, he saw James son of <seg type="lb" n="17" />
					    Zebedee and his brother John <seg type="lb" n="18" /> in a boat, preparing their nets.</seg>
					<seg n="20" type="verse">Without delay he called <seg type="lb" n="19" /> them, and they left their father
					     Zebedee in the boat <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="73r" /> with the hired men and followed him.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p>	
					<seg n="21" type="verse">They went to <seg type="lb" n="1" /> Capernaum, and when the Sabbath came,
					       Jesus went into the synagogue <seg type="lb" n="2" /> and began to teach.</seg>
					<seg n="22" type="verse">The people were amazed at his teaching <seg type="lb" n="3" />, because he taught
					      them as one who had authority, <seg type="lb" n="4" /> not as the teachers of the law.</seg>
					<seg n="23" type="verse">Just then a man in their synagogue <seg type="lb" n="5" /> who was possessed
					      by an impure spirit cried out, <seg type="lb" n="6" /></seg>
					<seg n="24" type="verse">“What do you want with us, Jesus of Nazareth? <seg type="lb" n="7" /> Have you
					      come to destroy us? I know who you are-the Holy One of God!” <seg type="lb" n="8" /></seg>
					<seg n="25" type="verse">“Be quiet!” said Jesus sternly. “Come out of him!” <seg type="lb" n="9" /></seg>
					<seg n="26" type="verse">The impure spirit shook the man violently <seg type="lb" n="10" /> and came out
					      of him with a shriek.</seg>
					<seg n="27" type="verse">The people <seg type="lb" n="11" /> were all so amazed that they asked <seg type="lb" n="12" />
					      each other, “What is this? A new teaching <seg type="lb" n="13" />-and with authority! He even gives orders
					      to impure spirits <seg type="lb" n="14" /> and they obey him.”</seg>
					<seg n="28" type="verse">News about <seg type="lb" n="15" /> him spread quickly over the whole region of
					     Galilee. <seg type="lb" n="16" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p>	
					<seg n="29" type="verse">As soon as they left the synagogue, they went <seg type="lb" n="17" /> with James
					      and John to the home of Simon <seg type="lb" n="18" /> and Andrew.</seg>
					<seg n="30" type="verse">Simon's mother-in-law <seg type="lb" n="19" /> was in bed with a fever, and they
					     immediately told Jesus about her. <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="73v" /></seg>
					<seg n="31" type="verse">So he went to her, took her hand <seg type="lb" n="1" /> and helped her up. The
					     fever left her and she began to wait on <seg type="lb" n="2" /> them.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="32" type="verse">That evening after sunset <seg type="lb" n="3" /> the people brought to Jesus
					      all the sick <seg type="lb" n="4" /> and demon-possessed. <seg type="lb" n="5" /></seg>
					<seg n="33" type="verse">The whole town gathered at the door, <seg type="lb" n="6" /></seg>
					<seg n="34" type="verse">and Jesus healed many who had various diseases.<seg type="lb" n="7" /> He also
					      drove out many demons, but <seg type="lb" n="8" /> he would not let the demons speak because they knew
					      who he was. <seg type="lb" n="9" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p>	
					<seg n="35" type="verse">Very early in the morning, while it was still dark, Jesus got up, left the house
					     and went off <seg type="lb" n="10" /> to a solitary place, where he prayed.</seg>
					<seg n="36" type="verse">Simon and <seg type="lb" n="11" /> his companions went to look for him,</seg>
					<seg n="37" type="verse">and <seg type="lb" n="12" /> when they found him, they exclaimed: <seg type="lb" n="13" />
					      “Everyone is looking for you!”</seg>
					<seg n="38" type="verse">Jesus replied, “Let us go somewhere else-<seg type="lb" n="14" /> to the nearby
					      villages-so I can preach there also. <seg type="lb" n="15" /> That is why I have come.”</seg>
					<seg n="39" type="verse">So he traveled throughout Galilee, preaching in their synagogues <seg type="lb" n="16" />
					     and driving out demons. <seg type="lb" n="17" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="40" type="verse">A man with leprosy came <seg type="lb" n="18" /> to him and begged him on his knees,
					     “If you are willing, you can make me clean.” <seg type="lb" n="19" /></seg>
					<seg n="41" type="verse">Jesus was indignant. He reached out his hand <seg type="lb" n="20" />
					    <seg type="pb" n="74r" /> and touched the man. “I am willing,” he said. “Be clean!”</seg>
					<seg n="42" type="verse">Immediately <seg type="lb" n="1" /> the leprosy left him and he was cleansed
					     <seg type="lb" n="2" />.</seg>
					<seg n="43" type="verse">Jesus sent him away at once with a strong warning:</seg>
					<seg n="44" type="verse"><seg type="lb" n="3" /> “See that you don't tell this to anyone. But go, show
					    <seg type="lb" n="4" /> yourself to the priest and offer the sacrifices <seg type="lb" n="5" /> that Moses
					    commanded for your cleansing, as a testimony to <seg type="lb" n="6" /> them.”</seg>
					<seg n="45" type="verse">Instead he went out and began to talk freely, spreading <seg type="lb" n="7" />
					     the news. As a result, Jesus could no longer <seg type="lb" n="8" /> enter a town openly but stayed outside
					     in lonely places. <seg type="lb" n="9" /> Yet the people still came to him from everywhere. <seg type="lb" n="10" /></seg>
				</p>	
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="chapter">
				<p>
					<seg n="1" type="verse">A few days later, when Jesus again entered Capernaum, <hi type="italics"> the people heard that
					     he had come home.</hi> <note type="gloss" place="margin"> Italicized text not found in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="2" type="verse">They gathered <seg type="lb" n="11" /> in such large numbers that there was no room left
					    <seg type="lb" n="12" /> not even outside the door, <seg type="lb" n="13" /> and he preached the word to them.</seg>
					<seg n="3" type="verse">Some men came, <seg type="lb" n="14" /> bringing to him a paralyzed man, <seg type="lb" n="15" />
					     carried by four of them.</seg>
					<seg n="4" type="verse">Since they could not <seg type="lb" n="16" /> get him to Jesus because of the
					     crowd, <seg type="lb" n="17" /> they made an opening in the roof above Jesus by digging through it
					    <seg type="lb" n="18" /> and then lowered the mat the man was lying on.</seg>
					<seg n="5" type="verse">When Jesus saw their faith <seg type="lb" n="19" />, he said to the paralyzed man,
					    “Son, <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="74v" /> your sins are forgiven.”</seg>
					<seg n="6" type="verse">Now some <seg type="lb" n="1" /> teachers of the law were sitting there, thinking to
					    <seg type="lb" n="2" /> themselves,</seg>
					<seg n="7" type="verse">“Why does this fellow talk like that? He's blaspheming! <seg type="lb" n="3" /> Who can forgive
					     sins but God alone?”</seg>
					<seg n="8" type="verse">Immediately <seg type="lb" n="4" /> Jesus knew in his spirit that this was what they were thinking
					     in their hearts, <seg type="lb" n="5" /> and he said to them, “Why are you thinking these <seg type="lb" n="6" /> things?</seg>
					<seg n="9" type="verse">Which is easier: to say to this paralyzed man, <seg type="lb" n="7" /> 'Your sins are forgiven,'
					     or to say, <seg type="lb" n="8" /> 'Get up, take your mat and walk'? <seg type="lb" n="9" /></seg>
					<seg n="10" type="verse">But I want you to know that the Son <seg type="lb" n="10" /> of Man has authority on earth to
					    forgive sins.” So he said to the <seg type="lb" n="11" /> man,</seg>
					<seg n="11" type="verse">“I tell you, get up, take your <seg type="lb" n="12" /> mat and go home.”</seg>
					<seg n="12" type="verse">He got up, took his mat <seg type="lb" n="13" /> and walked out in full view of them all
					     <seg type="lb" n="14" />. This amazed everyone and they praised God, saying <seg type="lb" n="15" />, “We have never
					     seen anything like this!” <seg type="lb" n="16" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="13" type="verse">Once again Jesus went out beside the lake. A large crowd <seg type="lb" n="17" /> came to him,
					     and he began to teach them.</seg>
					<seg n="14" type="verse">As he walked along <seg type="lb" n="18" />, he saw Levi son of Alphaeus sitting at the tax
					    collector's <seg type="lb" n="19" /> booth. “Follow me,” Jesus told him, and Levi got up and followed him <seg type="lb" n="20" />
					    <seg type="pb" n="75r" /></seg>
					<seg n="15" type="verse">While Jesus was having dinner at Levi's house <seg type="lb" n="1" />, many tax collectors and sinners
					      were eating <seg type="lb" n="2" /> with him and his disciples, for there were <seg type="lb" n="3" /> many who followed him.</seg>
					<seg n="16" type="verse">When the teachers of the law who were Pharisees <seg type="lb" n="4" /> saw him eating with the
					     sinners <seg type="lb" n="5" /> and tax collectors, they asked his disciples: <seg type="lb" n="6" /> “Why does he eat with
					    tax collectors <seg type="lb" n="7" /> and sinners?”</seg>
					<seg n="17" type="verse">On hearing this, Jesus <seg type="lb" n="8" /> said to them, “It is not the healthy who need a
					    doctor, but the sick. <seg type="lb" n="9" /> I have not come to call the righteous, but sinners.” <seg type="lb" n="10" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="18" type="verse">Now John's disciples and the Pharisees <seg type="lb" n="11" /> were fasting. Some people came
					    and asked Jesus, “How is it that <seg type="lb" n="12" /> John's disciples and the disciples of the Pharisees are fasting,
					<seg type="lb" n="13" /> but yours are not?”</seg>
					<seg n="19" type="verse">Jesus answered, <seg type="lb" n="14" /> “How can the guests of the bridegroom fast <seg type="lb" n="15" />
					     while he is with them? They cannot, <seg type="lb" n="16" /> so long as they have him with them. <seg type="lb" n="17" /></seg>
					<seg n="20" type="verse">But the time will come when the bridegroom will be taken <seg type="lb" n="18" /> from them,
					    and on that day they <seg type="lb" n="19" /> will fast.</seg>
					<seg n="21" type="verse">“No one sews a patch <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="76v" /> of unshrunk cloth on an old
					    garment. Otherwise, <seg type="lb" n="1" /> the new piece will pull away from the old, making the <seg type="lb" n="2" /> tear worse.</seg>
					<seg n="22" type="verse">And no one pours new wine into <seg type="lb" n="3" /> old wineskins. Otherwise, the wine will burst
					    the skins, <seg type="lb" n="4" /> and both the wine and the wineskins will be ruined. No, <seg type="lb" n="5" /> they pour
					    new wine into new wineskins.” <seg type="lb" n="6" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="23" type="verse">One Sabbath Jesus was going through <seg type="lb" n="7" /> the grainfields, and as his disciples walked along,
					      they began <seg type="lb" n="8" /> to pick some heads of grain.</seg>
					<seg n="24" type="verse">The Pharisees <seg type="lb" n="9" /> said to him, “Look, why are they doing what is <seg type="lb" n="10" />
					    unlawful on the Sabbath?”</seg>
					<seg n="25" type="verse">He answered, “Have you never <seg type="lb" n="11" /> read what David did when he and his companions
					    <seg type="lb" n="12" /> were hungry and in need? <seg type="lb" n="13" /></seg>
					<seg n="26" type="verse">In the days of Abiathar the high priest, he entered the house of God <seg type="lb" n="14" /> and ate the
					    consecrated bread, <seg type="lb" n="15" /> which is lawful <seg type="lb" n="16" /> only for priests to eat. And he also gave some
					    <seg type="lb" n="17" /> to his companions.”</seg>
					<seg n="27" type="verse">Then he said to them, “The Sabbath <seg type="lb" n="18" /> was made for man, not man <seg type="lb" n="19" />
					      for the Sabbath.</seg>
					<seg n="28" type="verse">So the Son of Man is Lord <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="77r" /> even of the Sabbath.”</seg>
				</p>	
                        </div>
                        <div n="3" type="chapter">
				<p> 
					<seg n="1" type="verse">Another time Jesus went <seg type="lb" n="1" /> into the synagogue, and a man with a shriveled hand
					    <seg type="lb" n="2" /> was there.</seg>
					<seg n="2" type="verse">Some of them were looking for a reason to accuse Jesus, <seg type="lb" n="3" /> so they watched
					      him closely to see if he would heal him on the Sabbath.</seg>
					<seg n="3" type="verse">Jesus said to the man with the shriveled <seg type="lb" n="4" /> hand, “Stand up in front of everyone.”</seg>
					<seg n="4" type="verse">Then Jesus asked <seg type="lb" n="5" /> them, “Which is lawful on the Sabbath: to do good or to do evil,
					    <seg type="lb" n="6" /> to save life or to kill?” But they remained silent. <seg type="lb" n="7" /></seg>
					<seg n="5" type="verse">He looked around at them in anger and, deeply distressed at their <seg type="lb" n="8" /> stubborn hearts,
					      said to the man, “Stretch out <seg type="lb" n="9" /> your hand.” He stretched it out, and <seg type="lb" n="10" /> his hand was
					      completely restored.</seg>
					<seg n="6" type="verse">Then the Pharisees <seg type="lb" n="11" /> went out and began to plot with the Herodians <seg type="lb" n="12" />
					     how they might kill Jesus.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="7" type="verse">Jesus withdrew with his disciples <seg type="lb" n="13" /> to the lake, and a large crowd from Galilee
					    <seg type="lb" n="14" /> followed.</seg>
					<seg n="8" type="verse">When they heard <seg type="lb" n="15" /> about all he was doing, many people came to  him from Judea,
					    <seg type="lb" n="16" /> Jerusalem, Idumea, and the regions  across the Jordan and <seg type="lb" n="17" /> around Tyre and Sidon.</seg>
					<seg n="9" type="verse">Because of the crowd he told his disciples <seg type="lb" n="18" /> to have a small boat ready for him,
					     to <seg type="lb" n="19" /> keep the people from crowding him.</seg>
					<seg n="10" type="verse">For he had healed many <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="76v" />, so that those with diseases were
					     pushing <seg type="lb" n="1" /> forward to touch him.</seg>
					<seg n="11" type="verse">Whenever the impure spirits <seg type="lb" n="2" /> saw him, they fell down before him and <seg type="lb" n="3" />
					     cried out, “You are the Son of God.”</seg>
					<seg n="12" type="verse">But he gave them strict <seg type="lb" n="4" /> orders not to tell others about him. <seg type="lb" n="5" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="13" type="verse">Jesus went up on a mountainside and called to him <seg type="lb" n="6" /> those he wanted, and they came to him.</seg>
					<seg n="14" type="verse">He appointed <seg type="lb" n="7" /> twelve that they might be with him and that he might send them
					    <seg type="lb" n="8" /> out to preach</seg>
					<seg n="15" type="verse">and to have authority <seg type="lb" n="9" /> to drive out demons. <seg type="lb" n="10" /></seg>
					<seg n="16" type="verse">These are the twelve he appointed <seg type="lb" n="11" />: Simon (to whom he gave the name Peter),
					    <seg type="lb" n="12" /></seg>
					<seg n="17" type="verse">James son of Zebedee and his brother John <seg type="lb" n="13" /> (to them he gave the name Boanerges,
					     which <seg type="lb" n="14" /> means “sons of thunder”),</seg>
					<seg n="18" type="verse">Andrew, Philip, <seg type="lb" n="15" /> Bartholomew, Matthew, Thomas, James <seg type="lb" n="16" /> son
					     of Alphaeus, Thaddaeus, Simon the Zealot <seg type="lb" n="17" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="19" type="verse">and Judas Iscariot, who betrayed him. <seg type="lb" n="18" /></seg>
					<seg n="20" type="verse">Then Jesus entered a house, and again a crowd gathered, <seg type="lb" n="19" /> so that he and his disciples
					     were not even able to eat.<seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="77r" /></seg>
					<seg n="21" type="verse">When his family heard about this, they went to take charge of him <seg type="lb" n="1" />, for they said,
					     “He is out of his mind.” <seg type="lb" n="2" /></seg>
					<seg n="22" type="verse">And the teachers of the law who came down from Jerusalem <seg type="lb" n="3" /> said, “He is possessed by
					     Beelzebul! By the prince <seg type="lb" n="4" /> of demons he is driving out demons.” <seg type="lb" n="5" /></seg>
					<seg n="23" type="verse">So Jesus called them over to him and began to speak to them in parables: <seg type="lb" n="6" /> “How can
					     Satan drive out Satan?</seg>
					<seg n="24" type="verse">If a kingdom is divided against <seg type="lb" n="7" /> itself, that kingdom cannot stand.</seg>
					<seg n="25" type="verse">If a house <seg type="lb" n="8" /> is divided against itself, that <seg type="lb" n="9" /> house cannot
					     stand.</seg>
					<seg n="26" type="verse">And if Satan opposes <seg type="lb" n="10" /> himself and is divided, he cannot stand; <seg type="lb" n="11" />
					    his end has come.</seg>
					<seg n="27" type="verse">In fact, no one can enter a strong <seg type="lb" n="12" /> man's house without first tying him up.
					    <seg type="lb" n="13" /> Then he can plunder the strong man's house. <seg type="lb" n="14" /></seg>
					<seg n="28" type="verse">Truly I tell you, people can be forgiven <seg type="lb" n="15" /> all their sins and every slander they
					    <seg type="lb" n="16" /> utter,</seg>
					<seg n="29" type="verse">but whoever blasphemes against the <seg type="lb" n="17" /> Holy Spirit will never be forgiven;
					    <seg type="lb" n="18" /> they are guilty of an eternal sin.”</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="30" type="verse">He said this because they were saying, <seg type="lb" n="19" /> “He has an impure spirit.”</seg>
					<seg n="31" type="verse">Then Jesus' mother and brothers arrived <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="77v" />. Standing outside,
					    they sent someone <seg type="lb" n="1" /> in to call him.</seg>
					<seg n="32" type="verse">A crowd was sitting around him <seg type="lb" n="2" />, and they told him, “Your mother and brothers
					    <seg type="lb" n="3" /> are outside looking for you.”</seg>
					<seg n="33" type="verse"><seg type="lb" n="4" /> “Who are my mother and my brothers?” he asked. <seg type="lb" n="5" /></seg>
					<seg n="34" type="verse">Then he looked at those seated in a circle around him <seg type="lb" n="6" /> and said, “Here are my mother
					    and my brothers!</seg>
					<seg n="35" type="verse">Whoever <seg type="lb" n="7" /> does God's will is my brother and <seg type="lb" n="8" /> sister and mother.”
					    <seg type="lb" n="9" /></seg>
				</p>	
                        </div>
                        <div n="4" type="chapter">
				<p> 
					<seg n="1" type="verse">Again Jesus began to teach by the lake. The crowd <seg type="lb" n="10" /> that gathered around him
					     was so large that he got into a boat and sat in it out on the <seg type="lb" n="11" /> lake, while all the people were along
					    the shore at the water's <seg type="lb" n="12" /> edge.</seg>
					<seg n="2" type="verse">He taught them many things by parables, and <seg type="lb" n="13" /> in his teaching said:</seg>
					<seg n="3" type="verse">“Listen! A farmer <seg type="lb" n="14" /> went out to sow his seed.</seg>
					<seg n="4" type="verse">As he was scattering <seg type="lb" n="15" /> the seed, some fell along the path, and
					    <seg type="lb" n="16" /> the birds came and ate it up.</seg>
					<seg n="5" type="verse">Some fell <seg type="lb" n="17" /> on rocky places, where it did not have much soil. <seg type="lb" n="18" />
					    It sprang up quickly, because <seg type="lb" n="19" /> the soil was shallow.</seg>
					<seg n="6" type="verse">But when <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="lb" n="78r" /> the sun came up, the plants were scorched,
					     and they withered because <seg type="lb" n="1" /> they had no root.</seg>
					<seg n="7" type="verse">Other seed fell among thorns, which <seg type="lb" n="2" /> grew up and choked the plants, so that
					    <seg type="lb" n="3" /> they did not bear grain.</seg>
					<seg n="8" type="verse">Still other seed fell on good soil. <seg type="lb" n="4" /> It came up, grew and produced a crop
					    <seg type="lb" n="5" />, some multiplying thirty, some sixty, some <seg type="lb" n="6" /> a hundred times.”</seg>
					<seg n="9" type="verse">Then Jesus said, “Whoever has ears to hear, let <seg type="lb" n="7" /> them hear.”</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="10" type="verse">When he was alone, <seg type="lb" n="8" /> the Twelve and the others around him asked him about the
					     <seg type="lb" n="9" /> parables.</seg>
					<seg n="11" type="verse">He told them, “The secret <seg type="lb" n="10" /> of the kingdom of God has been given to you. But
					     to those on the outside <seg type="lb" n="11" /> everything is said in parables</seg>
					<seg n="12" type="verse">so that,“'they may be ever seeing <seg type="lb" n="12" /> but never perceiving, and ever hearing but
					     <seg type="lb" n="13" /> never understanding; otherwise they might turn and be <seg type="lb" n="14" /> forgiven!'”</seg>
					<seg n="13" type="verse">Then Jesus said to them, “Don't you understand this parable <seg type="lb" n="15" />? How then will
					     you understand any parable? <seg type="lb" n="16" /></seg>
					<seg n="14" type="verse">The farmer sows the word.</seg>
					<seg n="15" type="verse">Some <seg type="lb" n="17" /> people are like seed along the path, where the word <seg type="lb" n="18" />
					     is sown. As soon as they hear it, Satan comes and takes away <seg type="lb" n="19" /> the word that was sown in them.
					    <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="78v" /></seg>
					<seg n="16" type="verse">Others, like seed sown on rocky places, <seg type="lb" n="1" /> hear the word and at once receive
					     it with joy <seg type="lb" n="2" />.</seg>
					<seg n="17" type="verse">But since they have no root, <seg type="lb" n="3" /> they last only a short time. When trouble
					    <seg type="lb" n="4" /> or persecution comes because of the word, <seg type="lb" n="5" /> they quickly fall away.</seg>
					<seg n="18" type="verse">Still others, like seed sown among thorns <seg type="lb" n="6" />, hear the word;</seg>
					<seg n="19" type="verse">but the worries <seg type="lb" n="7" /> of this life, the deceitfulness of wealth and the desires
					     for other things come in <seg type="lb" n="8" /> and choke the word, <seg type="lb" n="9" /> making it unfruitful.</seg>
					<seg n="20" type="verse">Others, like seed sown on <seg type="lb" n="10" /> good soil, hear the word, <seg type="lb" n="11" />
					    accept it, and produce a crop-some thirty <seg type="lb" n="12" />, some sixty, some a hundred times what was sown.”</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="21" type="verse">He said to them, “Do <seg type="lb" n="13" /> you bring in a lamp to put it <seg type="lb" n="14" />
					     under a bowl or a bed? Instead, don't you put it on its stand? <seg type="lb" n="15" /></seg>
					<seg n="22" type="verse">For whatever is hidden is meant to be disclosed, <seg type="lb" n="16" /> and whatever is concealed
					     is meant to be brought out <seg type="lb" n="17" /> into the open.</seg>
					<seg n="23" type="verse">If anyone has ears to hear, let them hear.” <seg type="lb" n="18" /></seg>
					<seg n="24" type="verse">“Consider carefully what you hear,” he continued. <seg type="lb" n="19" /> “With the measure you use,
					     it will be measured to <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="79r" /> you-and even more.</seg>
					<seg n="25" type="verse">Whoever has will be given <seg type="lb" n="1" /> more; whoever does not have, even what they have
					     will be taken <seg type="lb" n="2" /> from them.”</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="26" type="verse">He also said, “This is what the kingdom of God is like <seg type="lb" n="3" />. A man scatters
					     seed on the ground. <seg type="lb" n="4" /></seg>
					<seg n="27" type="verse">Night and day, whether he sleeps or gets up, the seed <seg type="lb" n="5" /> sprouts and grows,
					    though he does not know how.</seg>
					<seg n="28" type="verse">All by itself <seg type="lb" n="6" /> the soil produces grain-first the stalk, then the head
					     <seg type="lb" n="7" />, then the full kernel in the head.</seg>
					<seg n="29" type="verse">As soon <seg type="lb" n="8" /> as the grain is ripe, he puts the sickle to it, because the
					     <seg type="lb" n="9" /> harvest has come.”</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="30" type="verse">Again he said, “What shall we say the <seg type="lb" n="10" /> kingdom of God is like, or what
					    parable shall we use to describe it? <seg type="lb" n="11" /></seg>
					<seg n="31" type="verse">It is like a mustard seed, which is the <seg type="lb" n="12" /> smallest of all seeds on earth.</seg>
					<seg n="32" type="verse">Yet when planted, <seg type="lb" n="13" /> it grows and becomes the largest of all garden plants,
					    <seg type="lb" n="14" /> with such big branches that the <seg type="lb" n="15" /> birds can perch in its shade.”</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="33" type="verse">With many similar parables <seg type="lb" n="16" /> Jesus spoke the word to them, as much as they
					     could <seg type="lb" n="17" /> understand.</seg>
					<seg n="34" type="verse">He did not say anything to them without using a parable <seg type="lb" n="18" />. But when he was
					     alone with his own disciples, he explained <seg type="lb" n="19" /> everything.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="35" type="verse">That day when evening came, he said to his disciples, <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="79v" />
					    Let us go over to the other side.</seg>
					<seg n="36" type="verse">Leaving the crowd behind <seg type="lb" n="1" />, they took him along, just as he was, in the boat.
					     There were also other <seg type="lb" n="2" /> boats with him.</seg>
					<seg n="37" type="verse">A furious squall came up, <seg type="lb" n="3" /> and the waves broke over the boat, so that it was
					    <seg type="lb" n="4" /> nearly swamped.</seg>
					<seg n="38" type="verse">Jesus was in the stern, <seg type="lb" n="5" /> sleeping on a cushion. The disciples woke him and
					    said to him, <seg type="lb" n="6" /> “Teacher, don't you care if we drown?” <seg type="lb" n="7" /></seg>
					<seg n="39" type="verse">He got up, rebuked the wind and said to the waves, <seg type="lb" n="8" /> “Quiet! Be still!” Then
					     the wind died down and it was  <seg type="lb" n="9" /> completely calm.</seg>
					<seg n="40" type="verse">He said to his disciples, “Why are you so afraid? <seg type="lb" n="10" /> Do you still have no faith?”</seg>
					<seg n="41" type="verse">They were terrified <seg type="lb" n="11" /> and asked each other, “Who is this? <seg type="lb" n="12" />
					     Even the wind and the waves obey him!” <seg type="lb" n="13" /></seg>
				</p>	
                        </div>
                        <div n="5" type="chapter">
				<p>
					<seg n="1" type="verse">They went across the lake to the region of the Gerasenes <seg type="lb" n="14" /></seg>
					<seg n="2" type="verse">When Jesus got out of the boat <seg type="lb" n="15" /> a man with an impure spirit came
					     from the tombs to meet him.</seg>
					<seg n="3" type="verse">This <seg type="lb" n="16" /> man lived in the tombs, and no one <seg type="lb" n="17" />
					    could bind him anymore, not even with a chain. <seg type="lb" n="18" /></seg>
					<seg n="4" type="verse">For he had often been chained hand and foot, but he tore the chains <seg type="lb" n="19" />
					     apart and broke the irons on his feet. <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="80r" /> No one was strong enough to
					     subdue him.</seg>
					<seg n="5" type="verse"><seg type="lb" n="1" /> Night and day among the tombs and in the hills <seg type="lb" n="2" />
					     he would cry out and cut himself with stones. <seg type="lb" n="3" /></seg>
					<seg n="6" type="verse">When he saw Jesus from a distance, he ran and fell on his knees in front <seg type="lb" n="4" />
					     of him.</seg>
					<seg n="7" type="verse">He shouted at the top of his voice, “What do you want with me <seg type="lb" n="5" />, Jesus,
					    Son of the Most High God? In God's name don't <seg type="lb" n="6" /> torture me!”</seg>
					<seg n="8" type="verse">For Jesus had said to him, “Come out of this man, you impure <seg type="lb" n="7" /> spirit!”</seg>
					<seg n="9" type="verse">Then Jesus asked him, <seg type="lb" n="8" /> “What is your name?” “My name is Legion,” he
					    replied, <seg type="lb" n="9" /> “for we are many.”</seg>
					<seg n="10" type="verse">And he begged Jesus again and again <seg type="lb" n="10" /> not to send them out of the
					     area.</seg>
					<seg n="11" type="verse">A large herd <seg type="lb" n="11" /> of pigs was feeding on the nearby hillside.
					    <seg type="lb" n="12" /></seg>
					<seg n="12" type="verse">The demons begged Jesus, “Send us among the <seg type="lb" n="13" /> pigs; allow us
					     to go into them.”</seg>
					<seg n="13" type="verse">He gave them <seg type="lb" n="14" /> permission, and the impure spirits came out and went
					    <seg type="lb" n="15" /> into the pigs. The herd, about two thousand in number, <seg type="lb" n="16" /> rushed down
					     the steep bank into the lake and were drowned. <seg type="lb" n="17" /></seg>
					<seg n="14" type="verse">Those tending the pigs ran off and reported this <seg type="lb" n="18" /> in the town and
					    countryside, and the people went out to see what <seg type="lb" n="19" /> had happened.</seg>
					<seg n="15" type="verse">When they came to Jesus, they saw the man <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="80v" />
					    who had been possessed by the legion of demons, sitting there, dressed <seg type="lb" n="1" /> and in his right mind;
					    and they were afraid.</seg>
					<seg n="16" type="verse">Those who had seen <seg type="lb" n="2" /> it told the people what had happened to the
					    <seg type="lb" n="3" /> demon-possessed man-and told about the pigs as well.</seg>
					<seg n="17" type="verse">Then the <seg type="lb" n="4" /> people began to plead with Jesus to leave their region.
					     <seg type="lb" n="5" /></seg>
					<seg n="18" type="verse">As Jesus was getting into the boat, the man <seg type="lb" n="6" /> who had been demon-possessed
					     begged to go <seg type="lb" n="7" /> with him.</seg>
					<seg n="19" type="verse">Jesus did not let him, but said, <seg type="lb" n="8" /> “Go home to your own people and
					    tell them <seg type="lb" n="9" /> how much the Lord has done for you, and how he has had mercy on you.”
					    <seg type="lb" n="10" /></seg>
					<seg n="20" type="verse">So the man went away and began to tell in the Decapolis how much <seg type="lb" n="11" />
					    Jesus had done for him. And all the people were amazed. <seg type="lb" n="12" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="21" type="verse">When Jesus had again crossed over by boat to the other side <seg type="lb" n="13" /> of the
					    lake, a large crowd gathered around him while he was <seg type="lb" n="14" /> by the lake.</seg>
					<seg n="22" type="verse">Then one of the synagogue leaders <seg type="lb" n="15" />, named Jairus, came, and when
					    he saw Jesus, he fell at <seg type="lb" n="16" /> his feet.</seg>
					<seg n="23" type="verse">He pleaded earnestly with him, <seg type="lb" n="17" /> “My little daughter is dying. Please
					    come and put your <seg type="lb" n="18" /> hands on her so that she will be healed and live.” <seg type="lb" n="19" /></seg>
					<seg n="24" type="verse">So Jesus went with him. A large crowd followed <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="81r" />
					    and pressed around him.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="25" type="verse">And a woman was there <seg type="lb" n="1" /> who had been subject to bleeding for
					    twelve years.</seg>
					<seg n="26" type="verse">She had <seg type="lb" n="2" /> suffered a great deal under the care of many doctors
					    <seg type="lb" n="3" /> and had spent all she had, yet instead of getting better <seg type="lb" n="4" /> she
					     grew worse.</seg>
					<seg n="27" type="verse">When she heard <seg type="lb" n="5" /> about Jesus, she came up behind him in the crowd
					    and touched <seg type="lb" n="6" /> his cloak,</seg>
					<seg n="28" type="verse">because she thought, “If <seg type="lb" n="7" /> I just touch his clothes, I will be healed.”</seg>
					<seg n="29" type="verse">Immediately <seg type="lb" n="8" /> her bleeding stopped and she felt <seg type="lb" n="9" />
					     in her body that she was freed from her suffering.</seg>
					<seg n="30" type="verse">At once <seg type="lb" n="10" /> Jesus realized that power had gone out from him.
					    <seg type="lb" n="11" /> He turned around in the crowd and asked, <seg type="lb" n="12" /> “Who touched my clothes?”</seg>
					<seg n="31" type="verse">“You see the people <seg type="lb" n="13" /> crowding against you,” his disciples answered,
					     “and yet you can ask, '<seg type="lb" n="14" /> Who touched me?' ”</seg>
					<seg n="32" type="verse">But Jesus kept looking around to see <seg type="lb" n="15" /> who had done it.</seg>
					<seg n="33" type="verse">Then the woman, <seg type="lb" n="16" /> knowing what had happened to her, came and
					    <seg type="lb" n="17" /> fell at his feet and, trembling with fear, told him the whole truth.</seg>
					<seg n="34" type="verse">He <seg type="lb" n="18" /> said to her, “Daughter, your faith has healed you. <seg type="lb" n="19" />
					    Go in peace and be freed from your suffering.”</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="35" type="verse">While <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="81v" /> Jesus was still speaking, some people
					    came from the house of Jairus, the synagogue leader. <seg type="lb" n="1" /> “Your daughter is dead,” they said. “Why
					    bother the <seg type="lb" n="2" /> teacher anymore?”</seg>
					<seg n="36" type="verse">Overhearing what they said <seg type="lb" n="3" />, Jesus told him, “Don't be afraid; just
					    <seg type="lb" n="4" /> believe.”</seg>
					<seg n="37" type="verse">He did not let anyone follow him <seg type="lb" n="5" /> except Peter, James and John the
					    brother of <seg type="lb" n="6" /> James.</seg>
					<seg n="38" type="verse">When they came to the home of the synagogue leader, Jesus saw a <seg type="lb" n="7" /> commotion,
					     with people crying and wailing loudly. <seg type="lb" n="8" /></seg>
					<seg n="39" type="verse">He went in and said to them, “Why all this commotion and wailing? The child <seg type="lb" n="9" />
					    is not dead but asleep.”</seg>
					<seg n="40" type="verse">But they laughed <seg type="lb" n="10" /> at him. After he put them all out, he took the child's
					    father <seg type="lb" n="11" /> and mother and the disciples who were with him, and went in <seg type="lb" n="12" /> where
					    the child was.</seg>
					<seg n="41" type="verse">He took her by the hand <seg type="lb" n="13" /> and said to her, “Talitha koum!” (which means
					    “Little girl, I say to you, <seg type="lb" n="14" /> get up!”).</seg>
					<seg n="42" type="verse">Immediately the girl stood up and began to walk <seg type="lb" n="15" /> around (she was twelve years old).
					    At this they were <seg type="lb" n="16" /> completely astonished.</seg>
					<seg n="43" type="verse">He gave strict orders <seg type="lb" n="17" /> not to let anyone know about this, and told them to
					    give her something to eat. <seg type="lb" n="18" /></seg>
				</p>	
                        </div>
                        <div n="6" type="chapter">
				<p> 
					<seg n="1" type="verse">Jesus left there and went to his hometown, accompanied by <seg type="lb" n="19" /> his disciples.</seg>
					<seg n="2" type="verse">When the Sabbath came <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="82r" />, he began to teach in
					    the synagogue, and many who heard him <seg type="lb" n="1" /> were amazed. “Where did this man get these things?” they
					    asked. <seg type="lb" n="2" /> “What's this wisdom that has been given him? What <seg type="lb" n="3" /> are these remarkable
					    miracles he is performing? <seg type="lb" n="4" /></seg>
					<seg n="3" type="verse">Isn't this the carpenter? Isn't this Mary's <seg type="lb" n="5" /> son and the brother of James,
					    Joseph, Judas and Simon? <seg type="lb" n="6" /> Aren't his sisters here with us?” And they took offense <seg type="lb" n="7" /> at him.</seg>
					<seg n="4" type="verse">Jesus said to them, “A prophet is not <seg type="lb" n="8" /> without honor except in his own town,
					    among his <seg type="lb" n="9" /> relatives and in his own home.”</seg>
					<seg n="5" type="verse">He could not <seg type="lb" n="10" /> do any miracles there, except lay his hands on a few
					    <seg type="lb" n="11" /> sick people and heal them.</seg>
					<seg n="6" type="verse"><seg type="lb" n="12" /> He was amazed at their lack of faith. Then Jesus went <seg type="lb" n="13" />
					    around teaching from village to village. <seg type="lb" n="14" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="7" type="verse">Calling the Twelve to him, he began to send them out two by two <seg type="lb" n="15" /> and gave them
					    authority over impure spirits.</seg>
					<seg n="8" type="verse">These were <seg type="lb" n="16" /> his instructions: “Take nothing for the journey except a staff-
					    <seg type="lb" n="17" /> no bread, no bag, no money in your belts. <seg type="lb" n="18" /></seg>
					<seg n="9" type="verse">Wear sandals but not an extra <seg type="lb" n="19" /> shirt.</seg>
					<seg n="10" type="verse">Whenever you enter a <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="82v" /> house, stay there until you
					    leave that town. <seg type="lb" n="1" /></seg>
					<seg n="11" type="verse">And if any place will not welcome you <seg type="lb" n="2" /> or listen to you, leave that place and
					    shake the <seg type="lb" n="3" /> dust off your feet as a testimony against them.” <seg type="lb" n="4" /></seg>
					<seg n="12" type="verse">They went out and preached that people should repent. <seg type="lb" n="5" /></seg>
					<seg n="13" type="verse">They drove out many demons and anointed <seg type="lb" n="6" /> many sick people with oil and healed
					    them.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="14" type="verse">King Herod heard <seg type="lb" n="7" /> about this, for Jesus' name had become well known <seg type="lb" n="8" />.
					    Some were saying, “John the Baptist has been raised from <seg type="lb" n="9" /> the dead, and that is why miraculous powers
					    are at work in him.” <seg type="lb" n="10" /></seg>
					<seg n="15" type="verse">Others said, “He is Elijah.” And still others <seg type="lb" n="11" /> claimed, “He is a prophet,
					    like one of the prophets of long ago.” <seg type="lb" n="12" /></seg>
					<seg n="16" type="verse">But when Herod heard this, he said, “John, <seg type="lb" n="13" /> whom I beheaded, has been raised from the dead!”</seg>
					<seg n="17" type="verse">For Herod <seg type="lb" n="14" /> himself had given orders to have John arrested, and he had him bound
					    <seg type="lb" n="15" /> and put in prison. He did this because of Herodias, his brother Philip's <seg type="lb" n="16" /> wife,
					    whom he had married. <seg type="lb" n="17" /></seg>
					<seg n="18" type="verse">For John had been saying to Herod, “It is not lawful for you <seg type="lb" n="18" /> to have your
					    brother's wife.”</seg>
					<seg n="19" type="verse">So Herodias <seg type="lb" n="19" /> nursed a grudge against John and wanted to kill him. But she was not
					    <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="83r" /> able to,</seg>
					<seg n="20" type="verse">because Herod feared John <seg type="lb" n="1" /> and protected him, knowing him to be a righteous and
					     holy man. When Herod <seg type="lb" n="2" /> heard John, he was greatly puzzled; yet he liked to <seg type="lb" n="3" /> listen
					    to him.</seg>
					<seg n="21" type="verse">Finally the opportune time came. On his birthday <seg type="lb" n="4" /> Herod gave a banquet for his high
					    officials and military commanders <seg type="lb" n="5" /> and the leading men of Galilee.</seg>
					<seg n="22" type="verse">When the daughter <seg type="lb" n="6" /> of Herodias came in and danced, she pleased <seg type="lb" n="7" />
					    Herod and his dinner guests. The king said to the girl, <seg type="lb" n="8" /> “Ask me for anything you want, and I'll give it to you.”</seg>
					<seg n="23" type="verse">And he promised <seg type="lb" n="9" /> her with an oath, “Whatever you ask I will give <seg type="lb" n="10" />
					    you, up to half my kingdom.”</seg>
					<seg n="24" type="verse">She went out <seg type="lb" n="11" /> and said to her mother, “What shall I ask for?” “The head of
					    <seg type="lb" n="12" /> John the Baptist,” she answered.</seg>
					<seg n="25" type="verse">At once the girl hurried in <seg type="lb" n="13" /> to the king with the request: “I want you
					    <seg type="lb" n="14" /> to give me right now the head of John the Baptist on a platter.” <seg type="lb" n="15" /></seg>
					<seg n="26" type="verse">The king was greatly distressed, but because of his oaths and <seg type="lb" n="16" /> his dinner guests,
					    he did not want to refuse <seg type="lb" n="17" /> her.</seg>
					<seg n="27" type="verse">So he immediately sent an executioner with orders to bring John's <seg type="lb" n="18" /> head.
					    The man went, beheaded John in the prison,</seg>
					<seg n="28" type="verse">and brought back his <seg type="lb" n="19" /> head on a platter. He presented <seg type="lb" n="20" />
					    <seg type="pb" n="83v" /> it to the girl, and she gave it to her mother. <seg type="lb" n="1" /></seg>
					<seg n="29" type="verse">On hearing of this, John's disciples came and took <seg type="lb" n="2" /> his body and laid it in a tomb.
					    <seg type="lb" n="3" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="30" type="verse">The apostles gathered around Jesus <seg type="lb" n="4" /> and reported to him all they had done and taught.
					    <seg type="lb" n="5" /></seg>
					<seg n="31" type="verse">Then, because so many people were coming and <seg type="lb" n="6" /> going that they did not even have a
					    chance to eat, he said to them <seg type="lb" n="7" />, “Come with me by yourselves to a quiet place and get <seg type="lb" n="8" />
					    some rest.”</seg>
					<seg n="32" type="verse">So they went away by themselves in a boat <seg type="lb" n="9" /> to a solitary place.</seg>
					<seg n="33" type="verse">But many who saw <seg type="lb" n="10" /> them leaving recognized them and ran on foot <seg type="lb" n="11" />
					    from all the towns and got there ahead of <seg type="lb" n="12" /> them.</seg>
					<seg n="34" type="verse">When Jesus landed and saw a large crowd, he <seg type="lb" n="13" /> had compassion on them, because they were
					    like sheep without a <seg type="lb" n="14" /> shepherd. So he began teaching them many things.</seg>
					<seg n="35" type="verse">By this <seg type="lb" n="15" /> time it was late in the day, so his disciples came to him. <seg type="lb" n="16" />
					    “This is a remote place,” they said, “and it's already very <seg type="lb" n="17" /> late.</seg>
					<seg n="36" type="verse">Send the people away so that they can go to the surrounding <seg type="lb" n="18" /> countryside and villages and
					    buy themselves something to eat.” <seg type="lb" n="19" /></seg>
					<seg n="37" type="verse">But he answered, “You give them something <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="84r" /> to eat.”
					    <seg type="lb" n="1" /></seg>
					<seg n="38" type="verse">“How many <seg type="lb" n="2" /> loaves do you have?” <seg type="lb" n="3" /> he asked. “Go and see.” When
					    they found out, they said, <seg type="lb" n="4" /> “Five-and two fish.”</seg>
					<seg n="39" type="verse">Then Jesus directed them <seg type="lb" n="5" /> to have all the people sit down in groups <seg type="lb" n="6" />
					    on the green grass.</seg>
					<seg n="40" type="verse">So they sat down <seg type="lb" n="7" /> in groups of hundreds and <seg type="lb" n="8" /> fifties.</seg>
					<seg n="41" type="verse">Taking the five loaves and the <seg type="lb" n="9" /> two fish and looking up to heaven, he gave thanks
					    <seg type="lb" n="10" /> and broke the loaves. Then he gave them to his disciples to distribute to <seg type="lb" n="11" /> the people.
					    He also divided the two fish among them all.</seg>
					<seg n="42" type="verse">They all ate <seg type="lb" n="12" /> and were satisfied,</seg>
					<seg n="43" type="verse">and the disciples <seg type="lb" n="13" /> picked up twelve basketfuls of broken pieces of <seg type="lb" n="14" />
					    bread and fish.</seg>
					<seg n="44" type="verse">The number <seg type="lb" n="15" /> of the men who had eaten was five thousand. <seg type="lb" n="16" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="45" type="verse">Immediately Jesus made his disciples get into the boat <seg type="lb" n="17" /> and go on ahead of him to
					    Bethsaida, <seg type="lb" n="18" /> while he dismissed the crowd. <seg type="lb" n="19" /></seg>
					<seg n="46" type="verse">After leaving them, he went up on a mountainside to pray. <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="84r" /></seg>
					<seg n="47" type="verse">Later that night, the boat was in the middle of the lake, <seg type="lb" n="1" /> and he was alone on land.</seg>
					<seg n="48" type="verse">He saw the disciples straining <seg type="lb" n="2" /> at the oars, because the wind was against
					    <seg type="lb" n="3" /> them. Shortly before dawn he went <seg type="lb" n="4" /> out to them, walking on the lake. He was about to
					    pass by <seg type="lb" n="5" /> them,</seg>
					<seg n="49" type="verse">but when they saw him walking <seg type="lb" n="6" /> on the lake, they thought he was a ghost. They cried out,
					    <seg type="lb" n="7" /></seg>
					<seg n="50" type="verse">because they all saw him and were terrified. <seg type="lb" n="8" /> Immediately he spoke to them and
					    <seg type="lb" n="9" /> said, “Take courage! It is I. Don't be afraid.” <seg type="lb" n="10" /></seg>
					<seg n="51" type="verse">Then he climbed into the boat with them, and the wind <seg type="lb" n="11" /> died down. They were completely
					    amazed,</seg>
					<seg n="52" type="verse">for they had not understood <seg type="lb" n="12" /> about the loaves; their hearts were <seg type="lb" n="13" />
					    hardened.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="53" type="verse">When they had crossed over, they <seg type="lb" n="14" /> landed at Gennesaret and anchored there.</seg>
					<seg n="54" type="verse">As soon as <seg type="lb" n="15" /> they got out of the boat, people recognized Jesus.
					    <seg type="lb" n="16" /></seg>
					<seg n="55" type="verse">They ran throughout that whole region <seg type="lb" n="17" /> and carried the sick on mats <seg type="lb" n="18" />
					    to wherever they heard he was. <seg type="lb" n="19" /></seg>
					<seg n="56" type="verse">And wherever he went-into villages, towns <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="85r" /> or countryside-they
					    placed the sick <seg type="lb" n="1" /> in the marketplaces. They begged him to let them touch <seg type="lb" n="2" /> even the edge of his
					    cloak, and all who touched <seg type="lb" n="3" /> it were healed.</seg>
				</p>	
                        </div>
                        <div n="7" type="chapter">
				<p>
					<seg n="1" type="verse">The Pharisees and some of <seg type="lb" n="4" /> the teachers of the law who had come from Jerusalem gathered
					    around Jesus <seg type="lb" n="5" /></seg>
					<seg n="2" type="verse">and saw some of his disciples <seg type="lb" n="6" /> eating food with hands that were <seg type="lb" n="7" /> defiled,
					    that is, unwashed.</seg>
					<seg n="3" type="verse">(The Pharisees <seg type="lb" n="8" /> and all the Jews do not eat unless they give their hands <seg type="lb" n="9" /> a
					    ceremonial washing, holding to the tradition of the <seg type="lb" n="10" /> elders.</seg>
					<seg n="4" type="verse">When they come from the marketplace they do not eat <seg type="lb" n="11" /> unless they wash. And they observe many other
					    traditions <seg type="lb" n="12" />, such as the washing of cups <seg type="lb" n="13" />, pitchers and kettles.</seg>
					<seg n="5" type="verse">So the Pharisees <seg type="lb" n="14" /> and teachers of the law asked Jesus, “Why don't your disciples <seg type="lb" n="15" />
					    live according to the tradition of the elders <seg type="lb" n="16" /> instead of eating their food with defiled <seg type="lb" n="17" /> hands?”</seg>
					<seg n="6" type="verse">He replied, <seg type="lb" n="18" /> “Isaiah was right when he prophesied about you hypocrites;<seg type="lb" n="19" />
					    as it is written: “'These people honor me with their lips, but their hearts <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="85v" /> are far from me.</seg>
					<seg n="7" type="verse">They worship me in vain; <seg type="lb" n="1" /> their teachings are merely human rules.' <seg type="lb" n="2" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="8" type="verse">You have let go of the commands of God <seg type="lb" n="3" /> and are holding on to human traditions.”
					     <seg type="lb" n="4" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> A portion of this verse is found in the Latin Vulgate but
					     not in the NIV translation. </note> <seg type="lb" n="5" /></seg>
					<seg n="9" type="verse">And he continued, “You have a fine way of setting aside the commands <seg type="lb" n="6" /> of God in order to observe
					    your own traditions!</seg>
					<seg n="10" type="verse">For Moses <seg type="lb" n="7" /> said, 'Honor your father <seg type="lb" n="8" /> and mother,' and, 'Anyone who curses
					    their father or mother is to be put to death.' <seg type="lb" n="9" /></seg>
					<seg n="11" type="verse">But you say that if anyone declares that what might have been used to help their father <seg type="lb" n="10" /> or mother
					     is Corban that is, <seg type="lb" n="11" /> devoted to God</seg>
					<seg n="12" type="verse">then you no longer let <seg type="lb" n="12" /> them do anything for their father or mother.</seg>
					<seg n="13" type="verse">Thus you nullify <seg type="lb" n="13" /> the word of God by your tradition <seg type="lb" n="14" /> that you have handed
					     down. And you do <seg type="lb" n="15" /> many things like that.”</seg>
					<seg n="14" type="verse">Again Jesus called the crowd to him and said, <seg type="lb" n="16" /> “Listen to me, everyone, and understand this.</seg>
					<seg n="15" type="verse">Nothing <seg type="lb" n="17" /> outside a person can defile <seg type="lb" n="18" /> them by going into them. Rather,
					     it is what comes out of <seg type="lb" n="19" /> a person that <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="86r" /> defiles them.”</seg>
					<seg n="16" type="verse"> <seg type="lb" n="1" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> This verse is found in the Latin Vulgate but not in the NIV translation. </note></seg>
					<seg n="17" type="verse">After he had left the crowd and entered the house, his disciples asked <seg type="lb" n="2" /> him about this parable.</seg>
					<seg n="18" type="verse">“Are <seg type="lb" n="3" /> you so dull?” he asked. “Don't you see that <seg type="lb" n="4" /> nothing that enters a
					    person <seg type="lb" n="5" /> from the outside can defile <seg type="lb" n="6" /> them?</seg>
					<seg n="19" type="verse">For it doesn't go into their heart but into their stomach, <seg type="lb" n="7" /> and then out of the body.” In saying
					     this, Jesus declared all foods clean.</seg>
					<seg n="20" type="verse">He went on <seg type="lb" n="8" />: “What comes out of a person is what defiles <seg type="lb" n="9" /> them.</seg>
					<seg n="21" type="verse">For it is from within, out of a person's heart, <seg type="lb" n="10" /> that evil thoughts come-sexual immorality,
					    <seg type="lb" n="11" /> theft, murder,</seg>
					<seg n="22" type="verse">adultery, <seg type="lb" n="12" /> greed, malice, deceit, lewdness, envy, slander, <seg type="lb" n="13" /> arrogance
					     and folly</seg>
					<seg n="23" type="verse">All these evils come <seg type="lb" n="14" /> from inside and defile a person.”</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="24" type="verse">Jesus left <seg type="lb" n="15" /> that place and went to the vicinity of Tyre. He entered <seg type="lb" n="16" /> a
					     house and did not want anyone to know it; yet he could not keep his presence <seg type="lb" n="17" /> secret.</seg>
					<seg n="25" type="verse">In fact, as soon as she heard about him, a woman whose <seg type="lb" n="18" /> little daughter was possessed by an
					    impure spirit came and fell <seg type="lb" n="19" /> at his feet.</seg>
					<seg n="26" type="verse">The woman was a <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="86v" /> Greek, born in Syrian Phoenicia. She begged Jesus
					    to drive the demon <seg type="lb" n="1" /> out of her daughter.</seg>
					<seg n="27" type="verse">“<seg type="lb" n="2" /> First let the children eat all they want,” he told her, “for it is not right <seg type="lb" n="3" />
					    to take the children's bread and toss it to the dogs.” <seg type="lb" n="4" /></seg>
					<seg n="28" type="verse">“Lord,” she replied, <seg type="lb" n="5" /> “even the dogs under the table eat the children's crumbs.” <seg type="lb" n="6" /></seg>
					<seg n="29" type="verse">Then he told her, “For such a reply, you may go; <seg type="lb" n="7" /> the demon has left your daughter.”</seg>
					<seg n="30" type="verse">She went <seg type="lb" n="8" /> home and found her child lying on <seg type="lb" n="9" /> the bed, and the
					    demon gone.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="31" type="verse">Then <seg type="lb" n="10" /> Jesus left the vicinity of Tyre and went through Sidon, down <seg type="lb" n="11" />
					    to the Sea of Galilee and into the region of the Decapolis. <seg type="lb" n="12" /></seg>
					<seg n="32" type="verse">There some people brought to him a man who was deaf and could hardly talk,<seg type="lb" n="13" /> and they begged
					    Jesus to place his hand on him.</seg>
					<seg n="33" type="verse">After he took <seg type="lb" n="14" /> him aside, away from the crowd, Jesus put his fingers <seg type="lb" n="15" />
					    into the man's ears. Then he spit and touched <seg type="lb" n="16" /> the man's tongue.</seg>
					<seg n="34" type="verse">He looked up to heaven and with a deep sigh <seg type="lb" n="17" /> said to him, “Ephphatha!” which means
					    “Be opened!”. <seg type="lb" n="18" /></seg>
					<seg n="35" type="verse">At this, the man's ears were opened, his tongue <seg type="lb" n="19" /> was loosened and he began to speak
					    <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="87r" /> plainly.</seg>
					<seg n="36" type="verse">Jesus commanded them not to tell anyone. But <seg type="lb" n="1" /> the more he did so, the more they kept
					    <seg type="lb" n="2" /> talking about it.</seg>
					<seg n="37" type="verse">People were overwhelmed with amazement. <seg type="lb" n="3" /> “He has done everything well,” they said.
					     “He even makes the deaf hear <seg type="lb" n="4" /> and the mute speak.”</seg>
				</p>	
                        </div>
                        <div n="8" type="chapter">
				<p> 
					<seg n="1" type="verse">During those days another <seg type="lb" n="5" /> large crowd gathered. Since they had nothing to eat, Jesus <seg type="lb" n="6" />
					    called his disciples to him and said,</seg>
					<seg n="2" type="verse">“I have compassion <seg type="lb" n="7" /> for these people; they have already been with me three days <seg type="lb" n="8" />
					    and have nothing to eat.</seg>
					<seg n="3" type="verse">If I send <seg type="lb" n="9" /> them home hungry, they will collapse <seg type="lb" n="10" /> on the way, because some of them
					     have come a long distance.” <seg type="lb" n="11" /></seg>
					<seg n="4" type="verse">His disciples answered, “But where in this <seg type="lb" n="12" /> remote place can anyone get enough bread to feed them?”
					    <seg type="lb" n="13" /></seg>
					<seg n="5" type="verse">“How many loaves do you have?” Jesus asked. <seg type="lb" n="14" /></seg>
					<seg n="6" type="verse">He told the crowd to sit down <seg type="lb" n="15" /> on the ground. When he had taken the seven <seg type="lb" n="16" /> loaves
					     and given thanks, he broke them and gave them to his disciples <seg type="lb" n="17" /> to distribute to the people, and they did <seg type="lb" n="18" />
					     so.</seg>
					<seg n="7" type="verse">They had a few small fish as well; <seg type="lb" n="19" /> he gave thanks for them also and told the disciples to distribute
					    them.</seg>
					<seg n="8" type="verse">The people ate <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="87v" /> and were satisfied. Afterward the <seg type="lb" n="1" />
					     disciples picked up seven basketfuls of broken pieces <seg type="lb" n="2" /> that were left over.</seg>
					<seg n="9" type="verse">About <seg type="lb" n="3" /> four thousand were present. After he had <seg type="lb" n="4" /> sent them away,</seg>
					<seg n="10" type="verse">he got into the boat with <seg type="lb" n="5" /> his disciples and went to the region of Dalmanutha. <seg type="lb" n="6" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="11" type="verse">The Pharisees came and began <seg type="lb" n="7" /> to question Jesus. To test him, they asked him for <seg type="lb" n="8" />
					    a sign from heaven.</seg>
					<seg n="12" type="verse">He sighed deeply and said, <seg type="lb" n="9" /> “Why does this generation ask for a sign? Truly I tell <seg type="lb" n="10" />
					    you, no sign will be given to it.”</seg>
					<seg n="13" type="verse">Then <seg type="lb" n="11" /> he left them, got back into the boat and crossed to the <seg type="lb" n="12" /> other side.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="14" type="verse">The disciples had forgotten to bring <seg type="lb" n="13" /> bread, except for one loaf they had with <seg type="lb" n="14" />
					    them in the boat.</seg>
					<seg n="15" type="verse">“Be careful,” Jesus warned them. <seg type="lb" n="15" /> “Watch out for the yeast of the Pharisees and that of Herod.”
					    <seg type="lb" n="16" /></seg>
					<seg n="16" type="verse">They discussed this with one another and said <seg type="lb" n="17" />, “It is because we have no bread.”</seg>
					<seg n="17" type="verse">Aware <seg type="lb" n="18" /> of their discussion, Jesus asked them: <seg type="lb" n="19" /> “Why are you talking about
					    having no bread? <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="88r" /> Do you still not see or understand? Are your <seg type="lb" n="1" /> hearts hardened?</seg>
					<seg n="18" type="verse">Do you have eyes but fail to see <seg type="lb" n="2" />, and ears but fail to hear? And don't you <seg type="lb" n="3" />
					    remember?</seg>
					<seg n="19" type="verse">When I broke the five loaves for <seg type="lb" n="4" /> the five thousand, how many <seg type="lb" n="5" /> basketfuls of
					    pieces did you pick up?”</seg>
					<seg n="20" type="verse">“And <seg type="lb" n="6" />when I broke the seven loaves for the four thousand, <seg type="lb" n="7" /> how many basketfuls
					    of pieces did you pick up?” <seg type="lb" n="8" /> They answered, “Seven.”</seg>
					<seg n="21" type="verse">He said to them, <seg type="lb" n="9" /> “Do you still not understand?” <seg type="lb" n="10" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="22" type="verse">They came to Bethsaida, and some people brought a blind man and <seg type="lb" n="11" /> begged Jesus to touch him.</seg>
					<seg n="23" type="verse">He took the blind man by the hand <seg type="lb" n="12" /> and led him outside the village. When he had spit on the man's
					    <seg type="lb" n="13" /> eyes and put his hands on him, Jesus asked, <seg type="lb" n="14" /> “Do you see anything?”</seg>
					<seg n="24" type="verse">He looked up and said, <seg type="lb" n="15" /> “I see people; they look like trees walking around.”</seg>
					<seg n="25" type="verse"><seg type="lb" n="16" /> Once more Jesus put his hands on the man's eyes. Then his eyes <seg type="lb" n="17" /> were opened,
					    his sight was restored, and he saw <seg type="lb" n="18" /> everything clearly.</seg>
					<seg n="26" type="verse"><seg type="lb" n="19" /> Jesus sent him home, saying <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="88v" /> “Don't even go into
					    the village.”<seg type="lb" n="1" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="27" type="verse">Jesus and his disciples went on to the villages <seg type="lb" n="2" /> around Caesarea Philippi. On the way he asked
					     them, <seg type="lb" n="3" /> “Who do people say I am?”</seg>
					<seg n="28" type="verse">They replied, <seg type="lb" n="4" /> “Some say John the Baptist; others say <seg type="lb" n="5" /> Elijah; and still
					    others, one of the prophets.”</seg>
					<seg n="29" type="verse">“But <seg type="lb" n="6" /> what about you?” he asked. “Who do you say I am?” <seg type="lb" n="7" /> Peter answered,
					    “You are the Messiah.”</seg>
					<seg n="30" type="verse">Jesus warned <seg type="lb" n="8" /> them not to tell anyone about him.</seg>
					<seg n="31" type="verse">He then began to teach <seg type="lb" n="9" /> them that the Son of Man must suffer many things <seg type="lb" n="10" />
					    and be rejected by the elders, <seg type="lb" n="11" /> the chief priests and the teachers of the law, and that he must be killed and after three
					    <seg type="lb" n="12" /> days rise again.</seg>
					<seg n="32" type="verse">He spoke plainly about this <seg type="lb" n="13" />, and Peter took him aside and began to rebuke <seg type="lb" n="14" />
					    him.</seg>
					<seg n="33" type="verse">But when Jesus turned and looked at his disciples <seg type="lb" n="15" />, he rebuked Peter. “Get behind
					    <seg type="lb" n="16" /> me, Satan!” he said. “You do not have in mind the concerns of God, <seg type="lb" n="17" /> but merely human concerns.”
					    <seg type="lb" n="18" /></seg>
					<seg n="34" type="verse">Then he called the crowd to him along with his disciples and said: <seg type="lb" n="19" /> “Whoever wants to be my
					    disciple must deny themselves and take up <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="89r" /> their cross and follow me.</seg>
					<seg n="35" type="verse">For whoever <seg type="lb" n="1" /> wants to save their life will lose it, <seg type="lb" n="2" /> but whoever loses
					    their life for <seg type="lb" n="3" /> me and for the gospel will save it. <seg type="lb" n="4" /></seg>
					<seg n="36" type="verse">What good is it for someone to gain <seg type="lb" n="5" /> the whole world, yet forfeit their soul? <seg type="lb" n="6" /></seg>
					<seg n="37" type="verse">Or what can anyone give in exchange for <seg type="lb" n="7" /> their soul?</seg>
					<seg n="38" type="verse">If anyone is ashamed of me <seg type="lb" n="8" /> and my words in this adulterous and <seg type="lb" n="9" /> sinful
					    generation, the Son of Man will be ashamed of them when <seg type="lb" n="10" /> he comes in his Father's glory with the holy angels.”
					    <seg type="lb" n="11" /></seg>
					<seg n="39" type="verse"><note type="gloss" place="margin"> This verse is found in the Latin Vulgate but not in the NIV translation.
					    </note><seg type="lb" n="12" /> <seg type="lb" n="13" /> <seg type="lb" n="14" /></seg>
				</p>	
                        </div>
                        <div n="9" type="chapter">
				<p> 
					<seg n="1" type="verse"><hi rend="italic"> And he said to them, “Truly I tell you, some who are standing here will not taste death before they see that the kingdom
					    of God has come with power.”</hi> <note type="gloss" place="margin"> Italicized text not in Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="2" type="verse">After six days Jesus took Peter <seg type="lb" n="15" />, James and John with him and led them up a high <seg type="lb" n="16" />
					    mountain, where they were all alone. There he was transfigured <seg type="lb" n="17" /> before them.<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:2 is Mark 9:1 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="3" type="verse">His clothes <seg type="lb" n="18" /> became dazzling white, whiter <seg type="lb" n="19" /> than anyone in the world
					    could bleach them. <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="89v" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:3 is Mark 9:2 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="4" type="verse">And there appeared before them Elijah and Moses <seg type="lb" n="1" />, who were talking with Jesus.<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:4 is Mark 9:3 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="5" type="verse">Peter said to Jesus, “Rabbi, <seg type="lb" n="2" /> it is good for us to be here. Let us put up three shelters
					    <seg type="lb" n="3" /> -one for you, one for Moses and one for Elijah.” <seg type="lb" n="4" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:5 is Mark 9:4 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="6" type="verse">He did not know <seg type="lb" n="5" /> what to say, they were so frightened.<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:6 is Mark 9:5 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="7" type="verse">Then a cloud appeared <seg type="lb" n="6" /> and covered them, and a voice came from the cloud: “This
					    <seg type="lb" n="7" /> is my Son, whom I love. Listen to him!”<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:7 is Mark 9:6 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="8" type="verse">Suddenly, when they looked around <seg type="lb" n="8" />, they no longer saw <seg type="lb" n="9" /> anyone
					    with them except Jesus.<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:8 is Mark 9:7 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
				</p>
				<p> 
					<seg n="9" type="verse">As they were coming down <seg type="lb" n="10" /> the mountain, Jesus gave them orders not to tell anyone
					    <seg type="lb" n="11" /> what they had seen until the Son of Man <seg type="lb" n="12" /> had risen from the dead. <seg type="lb" n="13" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:9 is Mark 9:8 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="10" type="verse">They kept the matter to themselves, discussing what <seg type="lb" n="14" /> “rising from the dead” meant.
					    <seg type="lb" n="15" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:10 is Mark 9:9 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="11" type="verse">And they asked him, “Why do the teachers of the law <seg type="lb" n="16" /> say that Elijah must come first?”<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:11 is Mark 9:10 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="12" type="verse">Jesus replied, <seg type="lb" n="17" /> “To be sure, Elijah does come first, <seg type="lb" n="18" /> and
					    restores all things. Why then is it written that <seg type="lb" n="19" /> the Son of Man must suffer much and be rejected? <seg type="lb" n="20" />
					    <seg type="pb" n="90r" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:12 is Mark 9:11 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="13" type="verse">But I tell you, Elijah has come, and they have done <seg type="lb" n="1" /> to him everything they wished, just
					    as it is written <seg type="lb" n="2" /> about him.” <seg type="lb" n="3" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:13 is Mark 9:12 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="14" type="verse">When they came to the other disciples, they saw a large crowd <seg type="lb" n="4" /> around them and the teachers
					     of the law arguing with them.<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:14 is Mark 9:13 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="15" type="verse">As soon as all the people <seg type="lb" n="5" /> saw Jesus, they were overwhelmed with wonder <seg type="lb" n="6" />
					     and ran to greet him.<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:15 is Mark 9:14 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="16" type="verse">“What <seg type="lb" n="7" /> are you arguing with them about?” he asked. <seg type="lb" n="8" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:16 is Mark 9:15 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="17" type="verse">A man in the crowd answered, “Teacher, I brought you <seg type="lb" n="9" /> my son, who is possessed by a
					     spirit that has robbed him of speech. <seg type="lb" n="10" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:17 is Mark 9:16 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="18" type="verse">Whenever it seizes him, it throws him <seg type="lb" n="11" /> to the ground. He foams at the mouth, gnashes
					    his teeth and becomes rigid. I asked <seg type="lb" n="12" /> your disciples to drive out the spirit, but they could not.”
					    <seg type="lb" n="13" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:18 is Mark 9:17 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="19" type="verse">“You unbelieving generation,” Jesus replied, <seg type="lb" n="14" /> “how long shall I stay with you?
					    <seg type="lb" n="15" /> How long shall I put up with you? Bring the boy to me.”<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:19 is Mark 9:18 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="20" type="verse">So they brought him. <seg type="lb" n="16" /> When the spirit saw Jesus, it immediately <seg type="lb" n="17" />
					     threw the boy into a convulsion. He fell to the ground and rolled around, foaming at the <seg type="lb" n="18" /> mouth.<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:20 is Mark 9:19 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="21" type="verse">Jesus asked the boy's father, “How <seg type="lb" n="19" /> long has he been like this?” “From childhood,”
					    <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="90v" /> he answered.<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:21 is Mark 9:20 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="22" type="verse">“It has often thrown him into fire or water <seg type="lb" n="1" /> to kill him. But if you can do anything,
					    <seg type="lb" n="2" /> take pity on us and help us.”<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:22 is Mark 9:21 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="23" type="verse">“'If you can'?” said Jesus. <seg type="lb" n="3" /> “Everything is possible for one who believes.” <seg type="lb" n="4" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:23 is Mark 9:22 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="24" type="verse">Immediately the boy's father exclaimed <seg type="lb" n="5" />, “I do believe; help me overcome my unbelief!”
					    <seg type="lb" n="6" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:24 is Mark 9:23 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="25" type="verse">When Jesus saw that a crowd <seg type="lb" n="7" /> was running to the scene, he rebuked the impure spirit.
					    <seg type="lb" n="8" /> “You deaf and mute spirit,” he said, “I command you, come out of him <seg type="lb" n="9" /> and never enter
					    him again.”<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:25 is Mark 9:24 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="26" type="verse">The spirit shrieked <seg type="lb" n="10" />, convulsed him violently and came out. The boy looked <seg type="lb" n="11" />
					     so much like a corpse that many said, <seg type="lb" n="12" /> “He's dead.”<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:26 is Mark 9:25 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="27" type="verse">But Jesus took him by the hand <seg type="lb" n="13" /> and lifted him to his feet, and he stood up.<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:27 is Mark 9:26 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="28" type="verse">After Jesus had gone <seg type="lb" n="14" /> indoors, his disciples asked him privately <seg type="lb" n="15" />,
					     “Why couldn't we drive it out?” <seg type="lb" n="16" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:28 is Mark 9:27 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="29" type="verse">He replied, “This kind can come out <seg type="lb" n="17" /> only by prayer.” <seg type="lb" n="18" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:29 is Mark 9:28 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="30" type="verse">They left that place and passed through Galilee. <seg type="lb" n="19" /> Jesus did not want anyone to know
					     where they were,<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:30 is Mark 9:29 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="31" type="verse">because he was teaching his disciples. <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="91r" /> He said to them,
					    “The Son of Man <seg type="lb" n="1" /> is going to be delivered into the hands of men. They will kill him, <seg type="lb" n="2" />
					     and after three days he will rise.”<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:31 is Mark 9:30 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="32" type="verse">But they did not understand what he meant and were afraid <seg type="lb" n="3" /> to ask him about it.
					     <seg type="lb" n="4" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:32 is Mark 9:31 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
				</p>
				<p> 
					<seg n="33" type="verse">They came to Capernaum. When he was in the house, <seg type="lb" n="5" /> he asked them, “What were you
					    arguing about on the road?” <seg type="lb" n="6" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:33 is Mark 9:32 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="34" type="verse">But they kept quiet because on the way they had argued <seg type="lb" n="7" /> about who was the greatest.<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:34 is Mark 9:33 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="35" type="verse">Sitting down <seg type="lb" n="8" />, Jesus called the Twelve and said, “Anyone who wants to be first
					    <seg type="lb" n="9" /> must be the very last, and the servant of all.” <seg type="lb" n="10" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:35 is Mark 9:34 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="36" type="verse">He took a little child whom he placed among them <seg type="lb" n="11" />. Taking the child in his arms,
					       he said to them, <seg type="lb" n="12" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:36 is Mark 9:35 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="37" type="verse">“Whoever welcomes one of these little children <seg type="lb" n="13" /> in my name welcomes me; and
					    whoever welcomes <seg type="lb" n="14" /> me does not welcome me but <seg type="lb" n="15" /> the one who sent me.”<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:37 is Mark 9:36 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="38" type="verse">“Teacher,” said John, <seg type="lb" n="16" /> “we saw someone driving out demons in your name
					    <seg type="lb" n="17" /> and we told him to stop, because he was not <seg type="lb" n="18" /> one of us.”<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:38 is Mark 9:37 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="39" type="verse">“Do not stop him,” Jesus said. <seg type="lb" n="19" /> “For no one who does a miracle in my name can
					     in the next moment <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="91v" /> say anything bad about me,<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:39 is Mark 9:38 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="40" type="verse">for whoever <seg type="lb" n="1" /> is not against us is for us.<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:40 is Mark 9:39 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="41" type="verse">Truly <seg type="lb" n="2" /> I tell you, anyone who gives you a cup of water in <seg type="lb" n="3" />
					     my name because you belong to <seg type="lb" n="4" /> the Messiah will certainly not lose their reward. <seg type="lb" n="5" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:41 is Mark 9:40 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="42" type="verse">“If anyone causes one of these <seg type="lb" n="6" /> little ones-those who believe in me-to stumble,
					    <seg type="lb" n="7" /> it would be better for them if a large millstone were hung around their neck <seg type="lb" n="8" />
					     and they were thrown into the sea.<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:42 is Mark 9:41 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="43" type="verse">If your hand causes <seg type="lb" n="9" /> you to stumble, cut it off. It is better for you
					    <seg type="lb" n="10" /> to enter life maimed than with two hands to go into hell, <seg type="lb" n="11" /> where the fire
					    never goes out.<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:43 is Mark 9:42 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="44" type="verse"><seg type="lb" n="12" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> This verse is found in the Latin Vulgate but not in the NIV translation. </note></seg>
					<seg n="45" type="verse"><seg type="lb" n="13" /> And if your foot causes you to stumble, cut it off. <seg type="lb" n="14" />
					      It is better for you to enter life crippled <seg type="lb" n="15" /> than to have two feet and be thrown into hell. <seg type="lb" n="16" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:45 is Mark 9:44 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="46" type="verse"><seg type="lb" n="17" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> This verse is found in the Latin Vulgate but not in the NIV translation. </note></seg>
					<seg n="47" type="verse">And if your eye causes you to stumble <seg type="lb" n="18" />, pluck it out. It is better for you to
					      enter <seg type="lb" n="19" /> the kingdom of God with one eye than to have two eyes <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="91r" />
					     and be thrown into hell,<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:47 is Mark 9:46 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="48" type="verse">where “'the worms that eat them do not <seg type="lb" n="1" /> die, and the fire is not quenched.'<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:48 is Mark 9: in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="49" type="verse">Everyone <seg type="lb" n="2" /> will be salted with fire. <seg type="lb" n="3" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:49 is Mark 9:48 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="50" type="verse">“Salt is good, but if it loses its saltiness, <seg type="lb" n="4" /> how can you make it salty again?
					     Have salt among yourselves, <seg type="lb" n="5" /> and be at peace with each other.” <seg type="lb" n="6" /><note type="gloss" place="margin"> Mark 9:50 is Mark 9:49 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
				</p>	
                        </div>
                        <div n="10" type="chapter">
				<p> 
					<seg n="1" type="verse">Jesus then left that place and went into the region of Judea <seg type="lb" n="7" /> and across the Jordan.
					      Again crowds of people came to him, and as was <seg type="lb" n="8" /> his custom, he taught them.</seg>
					<seg n="2" type="verse">Some Pharisees came <seg type="lb" n="9" /> and tested him by asking, “Is it lawful for a man
					    <seg type="lb" n="10" /> to divorce his wife?”</seg>
					<seg n="3" type="verse">“What did <seg type="lb" n="11" /> Moses command you?” he replied.</seg>
					<seg n="4" type="verse">They said, “Moses permitted <seg type="lb" n="12" /> a man to write a certificate of divorce
					     and send her away.”</seg>
					<seg n="5" type="verse">“It was <seg type="lb" n="13" /> because your hearts were hard <seg type="lb" n="14" /> that Moses
					     wrote you this law,” Jesus replied.</seg>
					<seg n="6" type="verse">“But at the beginning <seg type="lb" n="15" /> of creation God 'made them male and female.'
					    <seg type="lb" n="16" /></seg>
					<seg n="7" type="verse">'For this reason a man will leave his father and mother <seg type="lb" n="17" /> and be united
					     to his wife,</seg>
					<seg n="8" type="verse">and the two <seg type="lb" n="18" /> will become one flesh.' So they are no longer two, but one
					    <seg type="lb" n="19" /> flesh.</seg>
					<seg n="9" type="verse">Therefore what God has joined together, let no one separate.” <seg type="lb" n="20" />
					    <seg type="pb" n="92v" /></seg>
					<seg n="10" type="verse">When they were in the house again, the disciples <seg type="lb" n="1" /> asked Jesus about this.
					       <seg type="lb" n="2" /></seg>
					<seg n="11" type="verse">He answered, “Anyone who divorces his wife <seg type="lb" n="3" /> and marries another woman commits
					     adultery against her.</seg>
					<seg n="12" type="verse">And if she divorces <seg type="lb" n="4" /> her husband and marries another man, she commits adultery.”
					     <seg type="lb" n="5" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p>
					<seg n="13" type="verse">People were bringing little children to Jesus for him to place his hands on them <seg type="lb" n="6" />,
					     but the disciples rebuked them. <seg type="lb" n="7" /></seg>
					<seg n="14" type="verse">When Jesus saw this, he was indignant. He said to <seg type="lb" n="8" /> them, “Let the little children
					      come to me, and do not hinder them, <seg type="lb" n="9" /> for the kingdom of God belongs to such as these. <seg type="lb" n="10" /></seg>
					<seg n="15" type="verse">Truly I tell you, anyone who will not receive <seg type="lb" n="11" /> the kingdom of God like a little
					    child will never <seg type="lb" n="12" /> enter it.”</seg>
					<seg n="16" type="verse">And he took the children in his arms, placed his hands <seg type="lb" n="13" /> on them and blessed them.
					     <seg type="lb" n="14" /></seg>
				</p>		
				<p> 	
					<seg n="17" type="verse">As Jesus started on his way, a man ran <seg type="lb" n="15" /> up to him and fell on his knees before him.
					     <seg type="lb" n="16" /> “Good teacher,” he asked, “what must I do to inherit <seg type="lb" n="17" /> eternal life?”</seg>
					<seg n="18" type="verse">“Why do you call me good?” Jesus answered. <seg type="lb" n="18" /> “No one is good-except God alone.</seg>
					<seg n="19" type="verse">You know <seg type="lb" n="19" /> the commandments: 'You shall not murder, <seg type="lb" n="20" />
					     <seg type="pb" n="93r" /> you shall not commit adultery, you shall not steal, you shall not give false testimony, you shall not
					      defraud, honor your father and mother. <seg type="lb" n="1" /></seg>
					<seg n="20" type="verse">“Teacher,” he declared, “all these <seg type="lb" n="2" /> I have kept since I was a boy.”</seg>
					<seg n="21" type="verse">Jesus looked at him <seg type="lb" n="3" /> and loved him. “One thing you lack,” he said. “Go, sell
					    <seg type="lb" n="4" /> everything you have and give to the poor <seg type="lb" n="5" />, and you will have treasure in heaven.
					    Then come, follow me.” <seg type="lb" n="6" /></seg>
					<seg n="22" type="verse">At this the man's face fell. He went away sad, <seg type="lb" n="7" /> because he had great wealth.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="23" type="verse">Jesus looked around <seg type="lb" n="8" /> and said to his disciples, “How hard <seg type="lb" n="9" />
					       it is for the rich to enter the kingdom of God!” <seg type="lb" n="10" /></seg>
					<seg n="24" type="verse"><hi rend="italic"> The disciples were amazed at his words. But Jesus said again, “Children, how hard it is to enter the
					     kingdom of God!</hi> <note type="gloss" place="margin"> Italicized text not found in Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					<seg n="25" type="verse">It is easier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle <seg type="lb" n="11" /> than for someone who
					     is rich to enter the kingdom of God.”</seg>
					<seg n="26" type="verse">The disciples were even more amazed <seg type="lb" n="12" />, and said to each other, “Who then can be
					    <seg type="lb" n="13" /> saved?”</seg>
					<seg n="27" type="verse">Jesus looked at them and said, “With man <seg type="lb" n="14" /> this is impossible, but not with God;
					    <seg type="lb" n="15" /> all things are possible with God.”</seg>
					<seg n="28" type="verse">Then Peter spoke up <seg type="lb" n="16" />, “We have left everything to follow
					     <seg type="lb" n="17" /> you!”</seg>
					<seg n="29" type="verse">“Truly I tell you,” Jesus replied, <seg type="lb" n="18" /> “no one who has left home or brothers
					    <seg type="lb" n="19" /> or sisters or mother or father or <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="93v" /> children or
					    fields for me and the gospel <seg type="lb" n="1" /></seg>
					<seg n="30" type="verse">will fail to receive a hundred times as much <seg type="lb" n="2" /> in this present age: homes,
					    brothers, sisters, <seg type="lb" n="3" /> mothers, children and fields-along with persecutions- <seg type="lb" n="4" />
					    and in the age to come eternal life. <seg type="lb" n="5" /></seg>
					<seg n="31" type="verse">But many who are first will be last, and the last <seg type="lb" n="6" /> first.”</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="32" type="verse">They were on their way up to Jerusalem, <seg type="lb" n="7" /> with Jesus leading the way, and
					    the disciples were astonished, while those who followed were afraid. <seg type="lb" n="8" /> Again he took the Twelve aside
					    and told them <seg type="lb" n="9" /> what was going to happen to him.</seg>
					<seg n="33" type="verse">“We are going up to Jerusalem,” <seg type="lb" n="10" /> he said, “and the Son of Man will be
					    delivered over to the chief <seg type="lb" n="11" /> priests and the teachers of the law. They will condemn him to death
					    and <seg type="lb" n="12" /> will hand him over to the Gentiles,</seg>
					<seg n="34" type="verse">who will mock <seg type="lb" n="13" /> him and spit on him, flog him <seg type="lb" n="14" /> and
					     kill him. Three days later he will rise.” <seg type="lb" n="15" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="35" type="verse">Then James and John, the sons of Zebedee, <seg type="lb" n="16" /> came to him. “Teacher,” they said,
					     “we want you to do for us whatever <seg type="lb" n="17" /> we ask.”</seg>
					<seg n="36" type="verse">“What do you want me to do for you?”<seg type="lb" n="18" /> he asked.</seg>
					<seg n="37" type="verse">They replied, “Let one of us sit at your right <seg type="lb" n="19" /> and the other at your left
					     <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="94r" /> in your glory.”</seg>
					<seg n="38" type="verse">“You don't know what you are asking,” Jesus said. <seg type="lb" n="1" /> “Can you drink the cup I
					     drink or be baptized with the baptism <seg type="lb" n="2" /> I am baptized with?”</seg>
					<seg n="39" type="verse">“We can,” they answered. <seg type="lb" n="3" /> Jesus said to them, “You will drink the cup
					    <seg type="lb" n="4" /> I drink and be baptized with the baptism <seg type="lb" n="5" /> I am baptized with,</seg>
					<seg n="40" type="verse">but to sit at my right <seg type="lb" n="6" /> or left is not for me to grant <seg type="lb" n="7" />.
					     These places belong to those for whom they have been prepared.” <seg type="lb" n="8" /></seg>
					<seg n="41" type="verse">When the ten heard about this, they became indignant with <seg type="lb" n="9" /> James and John.</seg>
					<seg n="42" type="verse">Jesus called them together and said, “You know that <seg type="lb" n="10" /> those who are regarded as
					      rulers of the Gentiles lord it over <seg type="lb" n="11" /> them, and their high officials exercise authority over <seg type="lb" n="12" /> them.</seg>
					<seg n="43" type="verse">Not so with you. Instead, <seg type="lb" n="13" /> whoever wants to become great among you must be your
					      servant, <seg type="lb" n="14" /></seg>
					<seg n="44" type="verse">and whoever wants to be first <seg type="lb" n="15" /> must be slave of all. <seg type="lb" n="16" /></seg>
					<seg n="45" type="verse">For even the Son of Man did not come <seg type="lb" n="17" /> to be served, but to serve, and to give his
					    <seg type="lb" n="18" /> life as a ransom for many.” <seg type="lb" n="19" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="46" type="verse">Then they came to Jericho. <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="94v" /> As Jesus and his disciples,
					     together with a large crowd, were leaving the city, a blind man, <seg type="lb" n="1" /> Bartimaeus (which means “son of Timaeus”),
					      was sitting by the roadside begging. <seg type="lb" n="2" /></seg>
					<seg n="47" type="verse">When he heard that it was Jesus of Nazareth, <seg type="lb" n="3" /> he began to shout, “Jesus, Son of David,
					       have mercy <seg type="lb" n="4" /> on me!”</seg>
					<seg n="48" type="verse">Many rebuked him and told him to be quiet, <seg type="lb" n="5" /> but he shouted all the more, “Son of
					      David, <seg type="lb" n="6" /> have mercy on me!”</seg>
					<seg n="49" type="verse">Jesus stopped and said, “Call him.” <seg type="lb" n="7" /> So they called to the blind man, “Cheer up!
					    <seg type="lb" n="8" /> On your feet! He's calling you.”</seg>
					<seg n="50" type="verse">Throwing his cloak aside, <seg type="lb" n="9" /> he jumped to his feet and came to Jesus.</seg>
					<seg n="51" type="verse">“What do you want me to do for you?” <seg type="lb" n="10" /> Jesus asked him. The blind man said, “Rabbi,
					     <seg type="lb" n="11" /> I want to see.”</seg>
					<seg n="52" type="verse">“Go,” said Jesus, “your faith has healed you.” <seg type="lb" n="12" /> Immediately he received his sight
						and <seg type="lb" n="13" /> followed Jesus along the road. <seg type="lb" n="14" /></seg>
				</p>	
                        </div>
                        <div n="11" type="chapter">
				<p> 
					<seg n="1" type="verse">As they approached Jerusalem and came to Bethphage and Bethany <seg type="lb" n="15" /> at the Mount of Olives,
						Jesus sent two of his disciples,</seg>
					 <seg n="2" type="verse">saying to them, <seg type="lb" n="16" /> “Go to the village ahead of you, and just as you enter it,
					     <seg type="lb" n="17" /> you will find a colt tied there, <seg type="lb" n="18" /> which no one has ever ridden. Untie it and
					     <seg type="lb" n="19" /> bring it here.</seg>
					 <seg n="3" type="verse">If anyone asks you, <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="95r" /> 'Why are you doing this?' say,
						'The Lord needs it <seg type="lb" n="1" /> and will send it back here shortly.'”</seg>
					 <seg n="4" type="verse">They <seg type="lb" n="2" /> went and found a colt outside in the street, tied <seg type="lb" n="3" />
					      at a doorway. As they untied it,</seg>
					 <seg n="5" type="verse">some people standing there asked, <seg type="lb" n="4" /> “What are you doing, untying that colt?”
					     <seg type="lb" n="5" /></seg>
					 <seg n="6" type="verse">They answered as Jesus had told them to, and the people let <seg type="lb" n="6" /> them go.</seg>
					 <seg n="7" type="verse">When they brought the colt to Jesus and threw <seg type="lb" n="7" /> their cloaks over it, he sat
					      on it.</seg>
					 <seg n="8" type="verse">Many <seg type="lb" n="8" /> people spread their cloaks on the road, while <seg type="lb" n="9" />
					       others spread branches they had cut in the fields. <seg type="lb" n="10" /> <note type="gloss" place="margin"> A portion of
					       this verse is found in the Latin Vulgate but not in the NIV translation. </note> <seg type="lb" n="11" /></seg>
					 <seg n="9" type="verse">Those who went ahead and those who followed shouted, <seg type="lb" n="12" /> “Hosanna!” “Blessed is
					      he who comes in the name of the Lord!”</seg>
					 <seg n="10" type="verse">“Blessed is the coming <seg type="lb" n="13" /> kingdom of our father David!” “Hosanna in the highest
					      heaven!” <seg type="lb" n="14" /></seg>
				</p>	 
				<p> 
					 <seg n="11" type="verse">Jesus entered Jerusalem and went into the temple courts. He looked around <seg type="lb" n="15" /> at
					     everything, but since it was already <seg type="lb" n="16" /> late, he went out to Bethany with the Twelve. <seg type="lb" n="17" /></seg>
					 <seg n="12" type="verse">The next day as they were leaving Bethany, Jesus was hungry.</seg>
					 <seg n="13" type="verse"><seg type="lb" n="18" /> Seeing in the distance a fig tree in leaf, he went <seg type="lb" n="19" />
						 to find out if it had any fruit. <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="95v" /> When he reached it, he found nothing but
					       leaves, <seg type="lb" n="1" /> because it was not the season for figs.</seg>
					 <seg n="14" type="verse">Then he said <seg type="lb" n="2" /> to the tree, “May no one ever eat fruit <seg type="lb" n="3" />
					       from you again.” And his disciples heard him say <seg type="lb" n="4" /> it.</seg>
				</p>		 
				<p> 	 
					 <seg n="15" type="verse">On reaching Jerusalem, Jesus entered the <seg type="lb" n="5" /> temple courts and began driving out
					       those who were buying and selling <seg type="lb" n="6" /> there. He overturned the tables of the money changers and the benches
					     <seg type="lb" n="7" /> of those selling doves,</seg>
					 <seg n="16" type="verse">and would not <seg type="lb" n="8" /> allow anyone to carry merchandise through <seg type="lb" n="9" />
					       the temple courts.</seg>
					 <seg n="17" type="verse">And as he taught them, he said, “Is it not written: <seg type="lb" n="10" /> 'My house will be called
					     <seg type="lb" n="11" /> a house of prayer for all nations'? But you have made it <seg type="lb" n="12" /> 'a den of robbers.'”
					      <seg type="lb" n="13" /></seg>
					 <seg n="18" type="verse">The chief priests and the teachers of the law <seg type="lb" n="14" />  heard this and began looking
					     for a way to kill him, <seg type="lb" n="15" /> for they feared him, because <seg type="lb" n="16" /> the whole crowd was amazed
					     at his teaching. <seg type="lb" n="17" /></seg>
				</p>	 
				<p> 	 
					 <seg n="19" type="verse"><hi rend="italic"> When evening came, Jesus and his disciples went out of the city.</hi>
						<note type="gloss" place="margin"> Italicized text not found in Latin Vulgate. </note></seg>
					 <seg n="20" type="verse">In the morning, as they went along, they saw the fig tree withered from the roots.
					     <seg type="lb" n="18" /></seg>
					 <seg n="21" type="verse">Peter remembered and said to Jesus, “Rabbi, look! The fig tree <seg type="lb" n="19" /> you cursed
						has withered!”</seg>
					 <seg n="22" type="verse">“Have faith in God,” <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="96r" /> Jesus answered.</seg>
					 <seg n="23" type="verse">“Truly I tell you, if anyone <seg type="lb" n="1" /> says to this mountain, 'Go, throw yourself into
					       the sea,' <seg type="lb" n="2" /> and does not doubt in their heart but believes <seg type="lb" n="3" /> that what they say
					      will happen, it will be done for them. <seg type="lb" n="4" /></seg>
					 <seg n="24" type="verse">Therefore I tell you, whatever <seg type="lb" n="5" /> you ask for in prayer, believe that you have
					      received it, and it will be <seg type="lb" n="6" /> yours.</seg>
					 <seg n="25" type="verse">And when you stand praying, <seg type="lb" n="7" /> if you hold anything against anyone <seg type="lb" n="8" />,
					      forgive them, so that your Father in heaven <seg type="lb" n="9" /> may forgive you your sins.” <seg type="lb" n="10" /></seg>
					 <seg n="26" type="verse"></seg>
				</p>	 
				<p> 	 
					 <seg n="27" type="verse">They arrived again in Jerusalem, and while Jesus was walking <seg type="lb" n="11" /> in the temple courts,
					      the chief priests, the teachers of the law <seg type="lb" n="12" /> and the elders came to him.</seg>
					 <seg n="28" type="verse">“By what authority are you doing <seg type="lb" n="13" /> these things?” they asked. “And who gave you
					      authority <seg type="lb" n="14" /> to do this?”</seg>
					 <seg n="29" type="verse">Jesus replied, “I will ask you <seg type="lb" n="15" /> one question. Answer me, and I will
					     <seg type="lb" n="16" /> tell you by what authority I am doing <seg type="lb" n="17" /> these things.</seg>
					 <seg n="30" type="verse">John's baptism-was it from heaven <seg type="lb" n="18" />, or of human origin? Tell me!”
					     <seg type="lb" n="19" /></seg>
					 <seg n="31" type="verse">They discussed it among themselves and said, “If we say, <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="96v" />
					       'From heaven,' he will ask, 'Then why didn't you believe <seg type="lb" n="1" /> him?'</seg>
					 <seg n="32" type="verse">But if we say, 'Of human origin' …” They feared the people, <seg type="lb" n="2" /> for everyone held that
					      John really <seg type="lb" n="3" /> was a prophet.</seg>
					 <seg n="33" type="verse">So they answered Jesus <seg type="lb" n="4" />, “We don't know.” Jesus said, “Neither will I
					     <seg type="lb" n="5" /> tell you by what authority I am doing these things.” <seg type="lb" n="6" /></seg>
				</p>	 
                        </div>
                        <div n="12" type="chapter">
				<p> 
					<seg n="1" type="verse">Jesus then began to speak to them in parables: “A man planted a vineyard. <seg type="lb" n="7" />
					      He put a wall around it, dug  a pit for the winepress <seg type="lb" n="8" /> and built a watchtower. Then he rented the
					      vineyard to some farmers <seg type="lb" n="9" /> and moved to another place.</seg>
					<seg n="2" type="verse">At harvest <seg type="lb" n="10" /> time he sent a servant to the tenants to collect from them
					     some of the fruit of <seg type="lb" n="11" /> the vineyard.</seg>
					<seg n="3" type="verse">But they seized him, beat him <seg type="lb" n="12" /> and sent him away empty-handed.</seg>
					<seg n="4" type="verse">Then he sent another <seg type="lb" n="13" /> servant to them; they struck this man on the
					      head and treated him shamefully. <seg type="lb" n="14" /></seg>
					<seg n="5" type="verse">He sent still another, and that one they killed. He sent many others; <seg type="lb" n="15" />
					    some of them they beat, others they killed.</seg>
					<seg n="6" type="verse">“He had one <seg type="lb" n="16" /> left to send, a son, whom he loved. He sent <seg type="lb" n="17" />
					     him last of all, saying, 'They will respect <seg type="lb" n="18" /> my son.'</seg>
					<seg n="7" type="verse">“But the tenants said to one another, <seg type="lb" n="19" /> 'This is the heir. Come,
					     let's kill him, and the <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="97r" /> inheritance will be ours.'</seg>
					<seg n="8" type="verse">So they took him and killed him, <seg type="lb" n="1" /> and threw him out of the vineyard.</seg>
					<seg n="9" type="verse">“What then will <seg type="lb" n="2" /> the owner of the vineyard do? He will come and kill
					     those tenants and give the vineyard <seg type="lb" n="3" /> to others.</seg>
					<seg n="10" type="verse">Haven't you read this passage of Scripture: “'The stone <seg type="lb" n="4" /> the builders
					     rejected has become the <seg type="lb" n="5" /> cornerstone; </seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="11" type="verse">the Lord has done this,<seg type="lb" n="6" /> and it is marvelous in our eyes'?” <seg type="lb" n="7" /></seg>
					<seg n="12" type="verse">Then the chief priests, the teachers of the law and the elders looked <seg type="lb" n="8" />
					     for a way to arrest him because they knew he had spoken the parable against them. But they were afraid of the crowd;
					    <seg type="lb" n="9" /> so they left him and went away.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="13" type="verse">Later they sent some <seg type="lb" n="10" /> of the Pharisees and Herodians to Jesus to catch
					     him <seg type="lb" n="11" /> in his words.</seg>
					<seg n="14" type="verse">They came to him and said, “Teacher, <seg type="lb" n="12" /> we know that you are a man of
					    integrity. You aren't swayed by others, <seg type="lb" n="13" /> because you pay no attention to who they are; but
					<seg type="lb" n="14" /> you teach the way of God in accordance with the truth. Is it right to pay <seg type="lb" n="15" />
					     the imperial tax to Caesar or not?</seg>
					<seg n="15" type="verse">Should we pay or shouldn't we?” But Jesus knew <seg type="lb" n="16" /> their hypocrisy. “Why are
					     you trying to trap me?” he asked. <seg type="lb" n="17" /> “Bring me a denarius and let me look at it.”</seg>
					<seg n="16" type="verse">They brought the coin <seg type="lb" n="18" />, and he asked them, “Whose image is this? And whose
					     inscription?” <seg type="lb" n="19" /> “Caesar's,” they replied.</seg>
					<seg n="17" type="verse">Then Jesus said <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="97v" /> to them, “Give back to Caesar
					     what is <seg type="lb" n="1" /> Caesar's and to God what is God's.” And they were amazed at him. <seg type="lb" n="2" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="18" type="verse">Then the Sadducees, who say there is no resurrection <seg type="lb" n="3" />, came to him with a
					     question. <seg type="lb" n="4" /></seg>
					<seg n="19" type="verse">“Teacher,” they said, “Moses wrote for us that if <seg type="lb" n="5" /> a man's brother dies
					     and leaves a wife <seg type="lb" n="6" /> but no children, the man must marry the widow <seg type="lb" n="7" /> and raise
					     up offspring for his brother.</seg>
					<seg n="20" type="verse">Now <seg type="lb" n="8" /> there were seven brothers. The first <seg type="lb" n="9" /> one married
					     and died without leaving any children. <seg type="lb" n="10" /></seg>
					<seg n="21" type="verse">The second one married the widow, but he also died, <seg type="lb" n="11" /> leaving no child. It was
					     the same with the third. <seg type="lb" n="12" /></seg>
					<seg n="22" type="verse">In fact, none of the seven left any <seg type="lb" n="13" /> children. Last of all, the woman died
					     too <seg type="lb" n="14" />.</seg>
					<seg n="23" type="verse">At the resurrection whose wife will <seg type="lb" n="15" /> she be, since the seven were
					    <seg type="lb" n="16" /> married to her?”</seg>
					<seg n="24" type="verse">Jesus replied, <seg type="lb" n="17" /> “Are you not in error because you do not know the Scriptures
					     <seg type="lb" n="18" /> or the power of God?</seg>
					<seg n="25" type="verse">When the dead rise <seg type="lb" n="19" />, they will neither marry nor be given in marriage;
					    <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="98r" /> they will be like the angels in heaven. <seg type="lb" n="1" /></seg>
					<seg n="26" type="verse">Now about the dead rising-have you not read <seg type="lb" n="2" /> in the Book of Moses, in the
					     account of the burning bush, <seg type="lb" n="3" /> how God said to him, 'I am the God of Abraham, <seg type="lb" n="4" />
					    the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob'?</seg>
					<seg n="27" type="verse">He is not the God of the dead, but of the living. <seg type="lb" n="5" /> You are badly mistaken!”
					     </seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="28" type="verse">One of the teachers of <seg type="lb" n="6" /> the law came and heard them debating. Noticing that
					     Jesus had given <seg type="lb" n="7" /> them a good answer, he asked <seg type="lb" n="8" /> him, “Of all the commandments,
					     which is the most important?” <seg type="lb" n="9" /></seg>
					<seg n="29" type="verse">“The most important <seg type="lb" n="10" /> one,” answered Jesus, “is this: 'Hear, O Israel: The
					     Lord <seg type="lb" n="11" /> our God, the Lord is one.</seg>
					<seg n="30" type="verse">Love the Lord your God with all <seg type="lb" n="12" /> your heart and with all your soul and with
					     all <seg type="lb" n="13" /> your mind and with all your <seg type="lb" n="14" /> strength.'</seg>
					<seg n="31" type="verse">The second is this: <seg type="lb" n="15" /> 'Love your neighbor as yourself.' There is no commandment
					    <seg type="lb" n="16" /> greater than these.”<seg type="lb" n="17" /> </seg>
					<seg n="32" type="verse">“Well said, teacher,” the man replied. “You are right in saying <seg type="lb" n="18" /> that God
					      is one and there is no other but him. <seg type="lb" n="19" /></seg>
					<seg n="33" type="verse">To love him with all your heart, with all your understanding <seg type="pb" n="20v" /> <seg type="pb" n="98v" />
					     and with all your strength, and to love <seg type="lb" n="1" /> your neighbor as yourself is more important than <seg type="lb" n="2" />
					    all burnt offerings and sacrifices.”</seg>
					<seg n="34" type="verse">When Jesus <seg type="lb" n="3" /> saw that he had answered wisely, <seg type="lb" n="4" /> he said
					    to him, “You are not far from the kingdom of God.” <seg type="lb" n="5" /> And from then on no one dared ask him any more questions.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="35" type="verse">While Jesus <seg type="lb" n="6" /> was teaching in the temple courts, he asked, “Why do the teachers
					     of the law say that the <seg type="lb" n="7" /> Messiah is the son of David?</seg>
					<seg n="36" type="verse">David himself, speaking <seg type="lb" n="8" /> by the Holy Spirit, declared: “'The Lord said to my
					     Lord: “Sit at my right hand until <seg type="lb" n="9" /> I put your enemies under <seg type="lb" n="10" /> your feet.”'</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="37" type="verse">David himself calls him 'Lord.' How then can he be his <seg type="lb" n="11" /> son?” The large crowd
					    listened to him with delight. <seg type="lb" n="12" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="38" type="verse">As he taught, Jesus said, “Watch out for the teachers of the law. <seg type="lb" n="13" /> They like
					    to walk around in flowing robes and be greeted with respect in the marketplaces, <seg type="lb" n="14" /></seg>
					<seg n="39" type="verse">and have the most important seats in the synagogues <seg type="lb" n="15" /> and the places of honor
					    at banquets. <seg type="lb" n="16" /></seg>
					<seg n="40" type="verse">They devour widows' houses and for a show make lengthy prayers. <seg type="lb" n="17" /> These men will
					    be punished most severely.”</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="41" type="verse">41 Jesus sat down <seg type="lb" n="18" /> opposite the place where the offerings were put
					    <seg type="lb" n="19" /> and watched the crowd putting their money into the temple treasury. <seg type="lb" n="20" />
					    <seg type="pb" n="99r" /> Many rich people threw in large amounts.</seg>
					<seg n="42" type="verse">But a <seg type="lb" n="1" /> poor widow came and put in <seg type="lb" n="2" /> two very small
					      copper coins, worth only a few cents.</seg>
					<seg n="43" type="verse">Calling <seg type="lb" n="3" /> his disciples to him, Jesus said, “Truly <seg type="lb" n="4" />
					      I tell you, this poor widow has put <seg type="lb" n="5" /> more into the treasury than all the others. <seg type="lb" n="6" /></seg>
					<seg n="44" type="verse">They all gave out of their <seg type="lb" n="7" /> wealth; but she, out of her poverty, put in
					     everything <seg type="lb" n="8" /> -all she had to live on.” <seg type="lb" n="9" /></seg>
				</p>	
                        </div>
                        <div n="13" type="chapter">
				<p> 
					<seg n="1" type="verse">As Jesus was leaving the temple, one of <seg type="lb" n="10" /> his disciples said to him, “Look,
					      Teacher! What massive stones! <seg type="lb" n="11" /> What magnificent buildings!”</seg>
					<seg n="2" type="verse">“Do you see <seg type="lb" n="12" /> all these great buildings?” replied Jesus. “Not one <seg type="lb" n="13" />
					      stone here will be left on another; every one will be thrown down.” <seg type="lb" n="14" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="3" type="verse">As Jesus was sitting on the Mount of Olives opposite <seg type="lb" n="15" /> the temple, Peter, James,
					      John and <seg type="lb" n="16" /> Andrew asked him privately,</seg>
					<seg n="4" type="verse">“Tell us, <seg type="lb" n="17" /> when will these things happen? And what will be the sign
					    <seg type="lb" n="18" /> that they are all about to be fulfilled?”</seg>
					<seg n="5" type="verse">Jesus said to them <seg type="lb" n="19" />: “Watch out that <seg type="lb" n="20" />
					    <seg type="lb" n="99v" /> no one deceives you.</seg>
					<seg n="6" type="verse">Many will come in my name <seg type="lb" n="1" />, claiming, 'I am he,' and will deceive many.
					    <seg type="lb" n="2" /></seg>
					<seg n="7" type="verse">When you hear of wars and rumors <seg type="lb" n="3" /> of wars, do not be alarmed. Such things
					       must happen, <seg type="lb" n="4" /> but the end is still to come.</seg>
					<seg n="8" type="verse">Nation will rise against <seg type="lb" n="5" /> nation, and kingdom against kingdom. There will
					    be <seg type="lb" n="6" /> earthquakes in various places, and famines. <seg type="lb" n="7" /> These are the beginning of
					    birth pains. <seg type="lb" n="8" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="9" type="verse">“You must be on your guard. You will be handed over <seg type="lb" n="9" /> to the local councils
					    and flogged in the synagogues. <seg type="lb" n="10" /> On account of me you will stand before governors and kings as witnesses
					    to them. <seg type="lb" n="11" /></seg>
					<seg n="10" type="verse">And <seg type="lb" n="12" /> the gospel must first be preached to all nations. <seg type="lb" n="13" /></seg>
					<seg n="11" type="verse">Whenever you are arrested and brought to trial, do not worry beforehand <seg type="lb" n="14" />
					    about what to say. Just say whatever is given you at the time, <seg type="lb" n="15" /> for it is not you speaking, but the
					    Holy Spirit. <seg type="lb" n="16" /></seg>
					<seg n="12" type="verse">“Brother will betray brother to death, and a father <seg type="lb" n="17" /> his child. Children
					    will rebel against their <seg type="lb" n="18" /> parents and have them put to death.</seg>
					<seg n="13" type="verse">Everyone will <seg type="lb" n="19" /> hate you because of me, but the one <seg type="lb" n="20" />
					    <seg type="pb" n="100r" /> who stands firm to the end will be saved. <seg type="lb" n="1" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="14" type="verse">“When you see 'the abomination that causes desolation' <seg type="lb" n="2" /> standing where it
					    does not belong-let the reader understand-<seg type="lb" n="3" /> then let those who are in Judea flee to the mountains.
					    <seg type="lb" n="4" /></seg>
					<seg n="15" type="verse">Let no one on the housetop go down <seg type="lb" n="5" /> or enter the house to take anything
					     out.</seg>
					<seg n="16" type="verse"><seg type="lb" n="6" /> Let no one in the field go back to get <seg type="lb" n="7" /> their
					    cloak.</seg>
					<seg n="17" type="verse">How dreadful it will be in those days for pregnant <seg type="lb" n="8" /> women and nursing
					    mothers! <seg type="lb" n="9" /></seg>
					<seg n="18" type="verse">Pray that this will not take place in winter, <seg type="lb" n="10" /></seg>
					<seg n="19" type="verse">because those will be days of distress <seg type="lb" n="11" /> unequaled from the beginning,
					    when God created the world, <seg type="lb" n="12" /> until now-and never to be equaled again. <seg type="lb" n="13" /></seg>
					<seg n="20" type="verse">“If the Lord had not cut short those days, no one would survive. But for the sake of the elect,
					    <seg type="lb" n="14" /> whom he has chosen, he has shortened them. <seg type="lb" n="15" /></seg>
					<seg n="21" type="verse">At that time if anyone says to you, 'Look, here is the Messiah!' or, 'Look, there he is!'
					    <seg type="lb" n="16" /> do not believe it.</seg>
					<seg n="22" type="verse">For false messiahs and false prophets <seg type="lb" n="17" /> will appear and perform signs and
					    wonders <seg type="lb" n="18" /> to deceive, if possible, even the elect.</seg>
					<seg n="23" type="verse">So <seg type="lb" n="19" /> be on your guard; I have told you everything ahead of time.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="24" type="verse">“But <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="lb" n="100v" /> in those days, following that distress,
					     “'the sun <seg type="lb" n="1" /> will be darkened, and the moon will not give its <seg type="lb" n="2" /> light;</seg>
					<seg n="25" type="verse">the stars will fall from the sky, <seg type="lb" n="3" /> and the heavenly bodies will be shaken.'
					    <seg type="lb" n="4" /></seg>
					<seg n="26" type="verse">“At that time people will see the Son of Man coming <seg type="lb" n="5" /> in clouds with great
					    power and glory. <seg type="lb" n="6" /></seg>
					<seg n="27" type="verse">And he will send his angels and gather his elect <seg type="lb" n="7" /> from the four winds, from
					    the ends of the earth to the <seg type="lb" n="8" /> ends of the heavens.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="28" type="verse">“Now learn this lesson from the fig tree: 9 As soon as its twigs get tender and its leaves 10 come
					    out, you know that summer 11  is near.</seg>
					<seg n="29" type="verse">Even so, when you see these <seg type="lb" n="12" /> things happening, you know that it is near,
					    right at the door. <seg type="lb" n="13" /></seg>
					<seg n="30" type="verse">Truly I tell you, this generation will certainly not pass away until all <seg type="lb" n="14" />
					    these things have happened.</seg>
					<seg n="31" type="verse">Heaven <seg type="lb" n="15" /> and earth will pass away, but my <seg type="lb" n="16" /> words will
					    never pass away. <seg type="lb" n="17" /></seg>
					<seg n="32" type="verse">“But about that day or hour no one knows, not even the angels in heaven, nor the Son, but only the
					    <seg type="lb" n="18" /> Father.</seg>
					<seg n="33" type="verse">Be on guard! Be alert! You do not know when that <seg type="lb" n="19" /> time will come.</seg>
					<seg n="34" type="verse">It's like a man going away: <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="b" n="101r" /> He leaves his house
					     and puts his servants <seg type="lb" n="1" /> in charge, each with their assigned task, <seg type="lb" n="2" /> and tells
					     the one at the door to keep watch. <seg type="lb" n="3" /></seg>
					<seg n="35" type="verse">“Therefore keep watch because you do not know when the owner of the house will come back-<seg type="lb" n="4" />
					     whether in the evening, or at midnight, or when the rooster crows, or at dawn.</seg>
					<seg n="36" type="verse">If he comes suddenly, <seg type="lb" n="5" /> do not let him find you sleeping.</seg>
					<seg n="37" type="verse">What I say <seg type="lb" n="6" /> to you, I say to everyone: 'Watch!'”</seg>
				</p>	
                        </div>
                        <div n="14" type="chapter">
				<p> 
					<seg n="1" type="verse">Now the Passover and <seg type="lb" n="7" /> the Festival of Unleavened Bread were only two days
					     away, <seg type="lb" n="8" /> and the chief priests and the teachers of the law were scheming <seg type="lb" n="9" /> to
					     arrest Jesus secretly and kill him.</seg>
					<seg n="2" type="verse">“But not during <seg type="lb" n="10" /> the festival,” they said, “or the people may riot.”
					    <seg type="lb" n="11" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="3" type="verse">While he was in Bethany, reclining at the table in the home of Simon the Leper, <seg type="lb" n="12" />
					    a woman came with an alabaster jar <seg type="lb" n="13" /> of very expensive perfume, made of pure nard. She broke the jar and
					     poured the perfume <seg type="lb" n="14" /> on his head.</seg>
					<seg n="4" type="verse">Some of those <seg type="lb" n="15" /> present were saying indignantly to <seg type="lb" n="16" /> one
					    another, “Why this waste of <seg type="lb" n="17" /> perfume?</seg>
					<seg n="5" type="verse">It could have been sold <seg type="lb" n="18" /> for more than a year's wages and the money given to
					     the poor.” <seg type="lb" n="19" /> And they rebuked her harshly.</seg>
					<seg n="6" type="verse">“Leave her alone,” said Jesus. <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="101v" /> “Why are you
					    bothering her? She has done a beautiful <seg type="lb" n="1" /> thing to me.</seg>
					<seg n="7" type="verse">The poor you will always have <seg type="lb" n="2" /> with you, and you can help them any time you
					     want. <seg type="lb" n="3" /> But you will not always have me. <seg type="lb" n="4" /></seg>
					<seg n="8" type="verse">She did what she could. She poured perfume <seg type="lb" n="5" /> on my body beforehand to prepare
					    for my burial.</seg>
					<seg n="9" type="verse">Truly I tell you <seg type="lb" n="6" />, wherever the gospel is preached <seg type="lb" n="7" />
					    throughout the world, what she has done <seg type="lb" n="8" /> will also be told, in memory of her.” <seg type="lb" n="9" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="10" type="verse">Then Judas Iscariot, one of the Twelve, went <seg type="lb" n="10" /> to the chief priests to
					    betray Jesus to them.</seg>
					<seg n="11" type="verse">They <seg type="lb" n="11" /> were delighted to hear this and promised to give him money.
					    <seg type="lb" n="12" /> So he watched for an <seg type="lb" n="13" /> opportunity to hand him over.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="12" type="verse">On the first day of the Festival of Unleavened Bread, <seg type="lb" n="14" /> when it was
					    customary to sacrifice the Passover lamb, Jesus' disciples asked <seg type="lb" n="15" /> him, “Where do you want us
					     to go and make preparations for you to eat the Passover?” <seg type="lb" n="16" /></seg>
					<seg n="13" type="verse">So he sent two of his disciples, telling them, <seg type="lb" n="17" /> “Go into the city,
					    and a man carrying a jar of <seg type="lb" n="18" /> water will meet you. Follow him.</seg>
					<seg n="14" type="verse">Say to the owner <seg type="lb" n="19" /> of the house he enters, 'The Teacher asks:
					     <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="102r" /> Where is my guest room, where I may eat the Passover with
					     <seg type="lb" n="1" /> my disciples?'</seg>
					<seg n="15" type="verse">He will show <seg type="lb" n="2" /> you a large room upstairs, furnished and ready. Make
					    preparations for us there.” <seg type="lb" n="3" /></seg>
					<seg n="16" type="verse">The disciples left, went into the city <seg type="lb" n="4" /> and found things just as
					    Jesus had told them. <seg type="lb" n="5" /> So they prepared the Passover. <seg type="lb" n="6" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="17" type="verse">When evening came, Jesus arrived with the Twelve. <seg type="lb" n="7" /></seg>
					<seg n="18" type="verse">While they were reclining at the table eating, he said, “Truly I tell you,
					     <seg type="lb" n="8" /> one of you will betray me-one who is eating with me.” <seg type="lb" n="9" /></seg>
					<seg n="19" type="verse">They were saddened, and one by one <seg type="lb" n="10" /> they said to him, “Surely you
					    don't mean me?”<seg type="lb" n="11" /></seg>
					<seg n="20" type="verse">“It is one of the Twelve,” he replied, “one who dips bread into the bowl with me.</seg>
					<seg n="21" type="verse"><seg type="lb" n="12" /> The Son of Man will go just as it is written about him.
					<seg type="lb" n="13" /> But woe to that man who betrays the Son of Man! <seg type="lb" n="14" /> It would be
					    better for him if he had not been born.” <seg type="lb" n="15" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="22" type="verse">While they were eating, Jesus took bread, and when he had given thanks, <seg type="lb" n="16" />
					    he broke it and gave it to his disciples, saying, “Take it; this is <seg type="lb" n="17" /> my body.”</seg>
					<seg n="23" type="verse">Then he took a cup, and when he had given thanks <seg type="lb" n="18" />, he gave it to
					    them, and they all drank from it.</seg>
					<seg n="24" type="verse">“This is <seg type="lb" n="19" /> my blood of the covenant, which is <seg type="lb" n="20" />
					    <seg type="pb" n="102v" /> poured out for many,” he said to them.</seg>
					<seg n="25" type="verse">“Truly I tell you, <seg type="lb" n="1" /> I will not drink again from the fruit of the
					    vine until that day <seg type="lb" n="2" /> when I drink it new in the kingdom <seg type="lb" n="3" /> of God.”</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="26" type="verse">When they had sung a hymn, they went out to the Mount of Olives.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="27" type="verse">“You 4 will all fall away,” Jesus told them, “for it is written: <seg type="lb" n="5" />
					    “'I will strike the shepherd, and <seg type="lb" n="6" /> the sheep will be scattered.'</seg>
					<seg n="28" type="verse">But after I have <seg type="lb" n="7" /> risen, I will go ahead of you into Galilee.”
					    <seg type="lb" n="8" /></seg>
					<seg n="29" type="verse">Peter declared, “Even if all fall away, <seg type="lb" n="9" /> I will not.”</seg>
					<seg n="30" type="verse">“Truly I tell you,” Jesus answered, <seg type="lb" n="10" /> “today-yes, tonight-before
					    the rooster crows twice you yourself <seg type="lb" n="11" /> will disown me three times.” <seg type="lb" n="12" /></seg>
					<seg n="31" type="verse">But Peter insisted emphatically, “Even if I have to die with you, <seg type="lb" n="13" />
					    I will never disown you.” And all the others said the same. <seg type="lb" n="14" /></seg>
					<seg n="32" type="verse">They went to a place called Gethsemane, <seg type="lb" n="15" /> and Jesus said to his
					    disciples, “Sit here while I pray.”</seg>
					<seg n="33" type="verse">He took <seg type="lb" n="16" /> Peter, James and John along with him, <seg type="lb" n="17" />
					    and he began to be deeply distressed and troubled. <seg type="lb" n="18" /></seg>
					<seg n="34" type="verse">“My soul is overwhelmed with sorrow to the point of death,” he said to them. “Stay here
					    and keep watch.” <seg type="lb" n="19" /></seg>
					<seg n="35" type="verse">Going a little farther, he fell to the ground <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="103r" />
					    and prayed that if possible the hour might <seg type="lb" n="1" /> pass from him.</seg>
					<seg n="36" type="verse">“Abba, Father,” he said, <seg type="lb" n="2" /> “everything is possible for you. Take this
					<seg type="lb" n="3" /> cup from me. Yet not what I will, but what <seg type="lb" n="4" /> you will.” </seg>
					<seg n="37" type="verse">Then he returned to his disciples and found them sleeping. <seg type="lb" n="5" /> “Simon,”
					    he said to Peter, “are you asleep? Couldn't <seg type="lb" n="6" /> you keep watch for one hour?</seg>
					<seg n="38" type="verse">Watch and pray so that you will not fall into temptation. <seg type="lb" n="7" /> The spirit
					    is willing, but the flesh <seg type="lb" n="8" /> is weak.”</seg>
					<seg n="39" type="verse">Once more he went away and prayed the <seg type="lb" n="9" /> same thing.</seg>
					<seg n="40" type="verse">When he came back, he again found <seg type="lb" n="10" /> them sleeping, because their eyes
					    were heavy. <seg type="lb" n="11" /> They did not know what to say to him. <seg type="lb" n="12" /></seg>
					<seg n="41" type="verse">Returning the third time, he said to them, “Are you still sleeping and resting?
					<seg type="lb" n="13" /> Enough! The hour has come. Look, the Son of <seg type="lb" n="14" /> Man is delivered into
					     the hands of sinners.</seg>
					<seg n="42" type="verse">Rise! Let us <seg type="lb" n="15" /> go! Here comes my betrayer!”</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="43" type="verse">Just as he <seg type="lb" n="16" /> was speaking, Judas, one of the Twelve, appeared. With
					<seg type="lb" n="17" /> him was a crowd armed with swords and clubs, sent from the chief priests <seg type="lb" n="18" />,
					     the teachers of the law, and the elders. <seg type="lb" n="19" /></seg>
					<seg n="44" type="verse">Now the betrayer had arranged a signal with them: <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="103v" />
					     “The one I kiss is the man; arrest <seg type="lb" n="1" /> him and lead him away under guard.”</seg>
					<seg n="45" type="verse">Going at once to <seg type="lb" n="2" /> Jesus, Judas said, “Rabbi!” and kissed <seg type="lb" n="3" />
					    him.</seg>
					<seg n="46" type="verse">The men seized Jesus <seg type="lb" n="4" /> and arrested him.</seg>
					<seg n="47" type="verse">Then one <seg type="lb" n="5" /> of those standing near drew his sword <seg type="lb" n="6" /> and
					    struck the servant of the high priest, cutting off his ear. <seg type="lb" n="7" /></seg>
					<seg n="48" type="verse">“Am I leading a rebellion,” said Jesus, “that you <seg type="lb" n="8" /> have come out with swords
					    and clubs to capture <seg type="lb" n="9" /> me?</seg>
					<seg n="49" type="verse">Every day I was with you, teaching in the temple courts <seg type="lb" n="10" />, and you did not
					    arrest me. But the <seg type="lb" n="11" /> Scriptures must be fulfilled.”</seg>
					<seg n="50" type="verse">Then everyone deserted <seg type="lb" n="12" /> him and fled.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="51" type="verse">A young man, wearing <seg type="lb" n="13" /> nothing but a linen garment, was following Jesus.
					    <seg type="lb" n="14" /> When they seized him,</seg>
					<seg n="52" type="verse">he fled naked, <seg type="lb" n="15" /> leaving his garment behind.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="53" type="verse">They took Jesus to the high priest <seg type="lb" n="16" /> , and all the chief priests, the elders
					     and the teachers <seg type="lb" n="17" /> of the law came together. <seg type="lb" n="18" /></seg>
					<seg n="54" type="verse">Peter followed him at a distance, right into the courtyard of <seg type="lb" n="19" /> the high
					    priest. There he sat with the guards and warmed himself <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="104v" /> at the fire.</seg>
					<seg n="55" type="verse">The chief priests and the whole <seg type="lb" n="1" /> Sanhedrin were looking for evidence against
					    Jesus so that they could put him to death, but they did not find any. <seg type="lb" n="2" /></seg>
					<seg n="56" type="verse">Many testified falsely against him, but their <seg type="lb" n="3" /> statements did not agree.</seg>
					<seg n="57" type="verse">Then some <seg type="lb" n="4" /> stood up and gave this false testimony <seg type="lb" n="5" />
					    against him:</seg>
					<seg n="58" type="verse">“We heard him say, <seg type="lb" n="6" /> 'I will destroy this temple made with human hands
					     <seg type="lb" n="7" /> and in three days will build another, not made <seg type="lb" n="8" /> with hands.'”</seg>
					<seg n="59" type="verse">Yet even then their testimony did not <seg type="lb" n="9" /> agree.</seg>
					<seg n="60" type="verse">Then the high priest stood up before them <seg type="lb" n="10" /> and asked Jesus, “Are you not
					     going to answer? <seg type="lb" n="11" /> What is this testimony that these men are bringing against you?” <seg type="lb" n="12" /></seg>
					<seg n="61" type="verse">But Jesus remained silent and <seg type="lb" n="13" /> gave no answer. Again the high priest
					     asked him, <seg type="lb" n="14" /> “Are you the Messiah, the Son of the Blessed One?” <seg type="lb" n="15" /></seg>
					<seg n="62" type="verse">“I am,” said Jesus. “And you will see the Son of Man sitting <seg type="lb" n="16" /> at the right
					     hand of the Mighty One and coming on the clouds of heaven.” <seg type="lb" n="17" /></seg>
					<seg n="63" type="verse">The high priest tore his clothes. <seg type="lb" n="18" /> “Why do we need any more witnesses?”
					     he asked.</seg>
					<seg n="64" type="verse">“You have heard <seg type="lb" n="19" /> the blasphemy. What do you think?” <seg type="lb" n="20" />
					    <seg type="pb" n="104r" /> They all condemned him as worthy of death. <seg type="lb" n="1" /></seg>
					<seg n="65" type="verse">Then some began to spit at <seg type="lb" n="2" /> him; they blindfolded him, struck him
					    <seg type="lb" n="3" /> with their fists, and said, “Prophesy!” And the guards took <seg type="lb" n="4" /> him and beat him.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="66" type="verse">While Peter was below in the courtyard, <seg type="lb" n="5" /> one of the servant girls of the
					    high priest came by. <seg type="lb" n="6" /></seg>
					<seg n="67" type="verse">When she saw Peter warming himself, she looked closely <seg type="lb" n="7" /> at him. “You also
					    were with that Nazarene, Jesus,” <seg type="lb" n="8" /> she said.</seg>
					<seg n="68" type="verse">But he denied it. “I don't know <seg type="lb" n="9" /> or understand what you're talking about,”
					    he said, <seg type="lb" n="10" /> and went out into the entryway.</seg>
					<seg n="69" type="verse">When the servant girl saw <seg type="lb" n="11" /> him there, she said again to those standing
					    around, <seg type="lb" n="12" /> “This fellow is one of them.”</seg>
					<seg n="70" type="verse">Again he denied it. <seg type="lb" n="13" /> After a little while, those standing near said to
					    <seg type="lb" n="14" /> Peter, “Surely you are one of them, for you are a Galilean.” <seg type="lb" n="15" /></seg>
					<seg n="71" type="verse">He began to call down curses, and he swore to them, <seg type="lb" n="16" /> “I don't know this
					    man you're talking about.”</seg>
					<seg n="72" type="verse">Immediately <seg type="lb" n="17" /> the rooster crowed the second time. Then Peter <seg type="lb" n="18" />
					    remembered the word Jesus had spoken to him: “Before the rooster <seg type="lb" n="19" /> crows twice you will disown me three times.”
					    And he broke down and wept. <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="lb" n="105v" /></seg>
				</p>	
                        </div>
                        <div n="15" type="chapter">
				<p> 
					<seg n="1" type="verse">Very early in the morning, <seg type="lb" n="1" /> the chief priests, with the elders, the teachers of the
					    law and <seg type="lb" n="2" /> the whole Sanhedrin, made their plans. So they bound Jesus, led him away <seg type="lb" n="3" />
					    and handed him over to Pilate.</seg>
					<seg n="2" type="verse">“Are you the king of the Jews?” <seg type="lb" n="4" /> asked Pilate. “You have said so,”
					    <seg type="lb" n="5" /> Jesus replied.</seg>
					<seg n="3" type="verse">The chief priests accused <seg type="lb" n="6" /> him of many things. <seg type="lb" n="7" /></seg>
					<seg n="4" type="verse">So again Pilate asked him, <seg type="lb" n="8" /> “Aren't you going to answer? See how many things
					    they are <seg type="lb" n="9" /> accusing you of.”</seg>
					<seg n="5" type="verse">But Jesus still made no <seg type="lb" n="10" /> reply, and Pilate was amazed. <seg type="lb" n="11" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="6" type="verse">Now it was the custom at the festival to release <seg type="lb" n="12" /> a prisoner whom the people
					    requested. <seg type="lb" n="13" /></seg>
					<seg n="7" type="verse">A man called Barabbas was in prison <seg type="lb" n="14" /> with the insurrectionists who had
					    committed murder in <seg type="lb" n="15" /> the uprising.</seg>
					<seg n="8" type="verse">The crowd <seg type="lb" n="16" /> came up and asked Pilate to do for them what he usually did.</seg>
					<seg n="9" type="verse">“Do you <seg type="lb" n="17" /> want me to release to you <seg type="lb" n="18" /> the king of
					    the Jews?” <seg type="lb" n="19" /> asked Pilate,</seg>
					<seg n="10" type="verse">knowing it <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="105v" /> was out of self-interest that the
					    <seg type="lb" n="1" /> chief priests had handed Jesus over to him.</seg>
					<seg n="11" type="verse">But the chief priests <seg type="lb" n="2" /> stirred up the crowd to have Pilate release Barabbas
					    instead. <seg type="lb" n="3" /></seg>
					<seg n="12" type="verse">“What shall I do, then, with the one <seg type="lb" n="4" /> you call the king of the Jews?” Pilate
					    <seg type="lb" n="5" /> asked them.</seg>
					<seg n="13" type="verse">“Crucify him!” <seg type="lb" n="6" /> they shouted.</seg>
					<seg n="14" type="verse"><hi rend="italic"> “Why? What crime has he committed?” asked Pilate. But they shouted all the louder,
						“Crucify him!”</hi> <note type="gloss" place="margin"> Italicized text not found in Latin Vulgate.</note></seg>
					<seg n="15" type="verse">Wanting to satisfy the crowd, <seg type="lb" n="7" /> Pilate released Barabbas to them.
					    <seg type="lb" n="8" /> He had Jesus flogged, and handed him over to be crucified. <seg type="lb" n="9" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="16" type="verse">The soldiers led Jesus away into the palace <seg type="lb" n="10" /> (that is, the Praetorium)
					    and called together the whole company of soldiers.</seg>
					<seg n="17" type="verse">They put <seg type="lb" n="11" /> a purple robe on him, then twisted together a crown of thorns
					    and <seg type="lb" n="12" /> set it on him.</seg>
					<seg n="18" type="verse">And they began to call out <seg type="lb" n="13" /> to him, “Hail, king of the Jews!”</seg>
					<seg n="19" type="verse">Again and again they struck him on the head <seg type="lb" n="14" /> with a staff and spit on him.
					    <seg type="lb" n="15" /> Falling on their knees, they paid homage to him. <seg type="lb" n="16" /></seg>
					<seg n="20" type="verse">And when they had mocked him, they took off <seg type="lb" n="17" /> the purple robe and put his
					    own clothes on him. <seg type="lb" n="18" /> Then they led him out to crucify him.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="21" type="verse">A certain man from <seg type="lb" n="19" /> Cyrene, Simon, <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="106r" />
					    the father of Alexander and Rufus, <seg type="lb" n="1" /> was passing by on his way in from the country, and they forced him
					    to carry the cross.</seg>
					<seg n="22" type="verse">They brought Jesus <seg type="lb" n="2" /> to the place called Golgotha which means <seg type="lb" n="3" />
					    “the place of the skull”.</seg>
					<seg n="23" type="verse">Then they offered him wine <seg type="lb" n="4" /> mixed with myrrh, but he did not take it.
					    <seg type="lb" n="5" /></seg>
					<seg n="24" type="verse">And they crucified him. Dividing up his clothes <seg type="lb" n="6" />, they cast lots to see what
					    each would get. <seg type="lb" n="7" /></seg>
					<seg n="25" type="verse">It was nine in the morning when they crucified him.</seg>
					<seg n="26" type="verse">The written notice of the charge against him read: THE KING <seg type="lb" n="9" /> OF THE JEWS.</seg>
					<seg n="27" type="verse">They crucified two rebels <seg type="lb" n="10" /> with him, one on his right and one on his left.
					    <seg type="lb" n="11" /></seg>
					<seg n="28" type="verse"><note type="gloss" place="margin"> This verse is found in the Latin Vulgate but not in
					    the NIV translation. </note><seg type="lb" n="12" /></seg>
					<seg n="29" type="verse">Those who passed by hurled <seg type="lb" n="13" /> insults at him, shaking their heads
					    <seg type="lb" n="14" /> and saying, “So! You who are going to destroy the temple <seg type="lb" n="15" /> and build it
					    in three days,</seg>
					<seg n="30" type="verse">come down <seg type="lb" n="16" /> from the cross and save yourself!” <seg type="lb" n="17" /></seg>
					<seg n="31" type="verse">In the same way the chief priests and <seg type="lb" n="18" /> the teachers of the law mocked him
					    among themselves. “He saved others,” they said, <seg type="lb" n="19" /> “but he can't save himself!</seg>
					<seg n="32" type="verse">Let this Messiah, this king <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="106v" /> of Israel, come
					    down now from the cross, that we may see <seg type="lb" n="1" /> and believe.” Those crucified with him also heaped insults
					    on <seg type="lb" n="2" /> him.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="33" type="verse">At noon, darkness <seg type="lb" n="3" /> came over the whole land until three in the <seg type="lb" n="4" />
					    afternoon.</seg>
					<seg n="34" type="verse"> And at three in the afternoon <seg type="lb" n="5" /> Jesus cried out in a loud voice, “Eloi,
					    Eloi, lema sabachthani?” (which means <seg type="lb" n="6" /> “My God, my God, why have you forsaken <seg type="lb" n="7" /> me?”).</seg>
					<seg n="35" type="verse">When some of those standing near heard this, they said, <seg type="lb" n="8" /> “Listen, he's
					    calling Elijah.”</seg>
					<seg n="36" type="verse">Someone ran, <seg type="lb" n="9" /> filled a sponge with wine vinegar, <seg type="lb" n="10" />
					    put it on a staff, and offered it to Jesus to drink. <seg type="lb" n="11" /> “Now leave him alone. Let's see if Elijah
					    comes to take <seg type="lb" n="12" /> him down,” he said.</seg>
					<seg n="37" type="verse">With a loud cry, Jesus breathed his last. <seg type="lb" n="13" /></seg>
					<seg n="38" type="verse">The curtain of the temple was torn in two <seg type="lb" n="14" /> from top to bottom. </seg>
					<seg n="39" type="verse">And when <seg type="lb" n="15" /> the centurion, who stood there in front of Jesus, saw how he died
					    <seg type="lb" n="16" />, he said, “Surely this man was the Son <seg type="lb" n="17" /> of God!”</seg>
					<seg n="40" type="verse">Some women were watching from a distance. <seg type="lb" n="18" /> Among them were Mary Magdalene,
					    <seg type="lb" n="19" /> Mary the mother of James the younger and of Joseph, <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="107r" />
					    and Salome.</seg>
					<seg n="41" type="verse">In Galilee these women had followed <seg type="lb" n="1" /> him and cared for his needs. Many
					    <seg type="lb" n="2" /> other women who had come up with him to Jerusalem were also there. <seg type="lb" n="3" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="42" type="verse">It was Preparation Day (that is, <seg type="lb" n="4" /> the day before the Sabbath). So as evening
					    approached, <seg type="lb" n="5" /></seg>
					<seg n="43" type="verse">Joseph of Arimathea, a prominent <seg type="lb" n="6" /> member of the Council, who was himself
					    waiting for the kingdom <seg type="lb" n="7" /> of God, went boldly to Pilate and asked for <seg type="lb" n="8" /> Jesus'
					    body.</seg>
					<seg n="44" type="verse">Pilate was surprised to hear that he was already <seg type="lb" n="9" /> dead. Summoning the
					    centurion, he asked <seg type="lb" n="10" /> him if Jesus had already died.</seg>
					<seg n="45" type="verse">When he learned <seg type="lb" n="11" /> from the centurion that it was so, he gave the body
					    to Joseph. <seg type="lb" n="12" /></seg>
					<seg n="46" type="verse">So Joseph bought some linen cloth, took down the body, <seg type="lb" n="13" /> wrapped it in
					    the linen, and placed it in a tomb <seg type="lb" n="14" /> cut out of rock. Then he rolled <seg type="lb" n="15" /> a
					    stone against the entrance of the tomb. <seg type="lb" n="16" /></seg>
					<seg n="47" type="verse">Mary Magdalene and Mary the mother <seg type="lb" n="17" /> of Joseph saw where he was laid.</seg>
				</p>	
                        </div>
                        <div n="16" type="chapter">
				<p> 
					<seg n="1" type="verse">When the <seg type="lb" n="18" /> Sabbath was over, Mary Magdalene, Mary the mother <seg type="lb" n="19" />
					    of James, and Salome bought spices so that they might go to <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="107v" /> anoint Jesus' body.</seg>
					<seg n="2" type="verse">Very early on the first day <seg type="lb" n="1" /> of the week, just after sunrise, they were on
					    their <seg type="lb" n="2" /> way to the tomb</seg>
					<seg n="3" type="verse">and they asked each other, “Who will roll the stone away <seg type="lb" n="3" /> from the entrance
					    of the tomb?” <seg type="lb" n="4" /></seg>
					<seg n="4" type="verse">But when they looked up, they saw that the stone <seg type="lb" n="5" />, which was very large, had
					    been rolled <seg type="lb" n="6" /> away.</seg>
					<seg n="5" type="verse">As they entered the tomb, they saw <seg type="lb" n="7" /> a young man dressed in a white robe sitting
					    on the right side, <seg type="lb" n="8" /> and they were alarmed.</seg>
					<seg n="6" type="verse">“Don't be alarmed,” he said. <seg type="lb" n="9" /> “You are looking for Jesus the Nazarene, who was
					    crucified. <seg type="lb" n="10" /> He has risen! He is not here. See the place where they laid <seg type="lb" n="11" /> him.</seg>
					<seg n="7" type="verse">But go, tell his disciples and <seg type="lb" n="12" /> Peter, 'He is going ahead of you into Galilee.
					    There <seg type="lb" n="13" /> you will see him, just as he told you.'”</seg>
					<seg n="8" type="verse">Trembling and bewildered <seg type="lb" n="14" />, the women went out and fled from the tomb.
					    <seg type="lb" n="15" /> They said nothing to anyone, <seg type="lb" n="16" /> because they were afraid.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="9" type="verse">When Jesus rose early on the first day of the week <seg type="lb" n="17" />, he appeared first to Mary
					    Magdalene, <seg type="lb" n="18" /> out of whom he had driven seven demons.</seg>
					<seg n="10" type="verse">She went <seg type="lb" n="19" /> and told those who had been with him and who were mourning
					    <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="108r" /> and weeping</seg>
					<seg n="11" type="verse">When they heard that <seg type="lb" n="1" /> Jesus was alive and that she had seen him, <seg type="lb" n="2" />
					    they did not believe it.</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="12" type="verse">Afterward Jesus appeared in a different form to two of them while they were walking <seg type="lb" n="3" />
					    in the country.</seg>
					<seg n="13" type="verse">These returned <seg type="lb" n="4" /> and reported it to the rest; but they did not believe them either.
					    <seg type="lb" n="5" /></seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="14" type="verse">Later Jesus appeared to the Eleven <seg type="lb" n="6" /> as they were eating; he rebuked them for their
					    lack of faith <seg type="lb" n="7" /> and their stubborn refusal <seg type="lb" n="8" /> to believe those who had seen him after he
					    had risen. <seg type="lb" n="9" /></seg>
					<seg n="15" type="verse">He said to them, “Go into all <seg type="lb" n="10" /> the world and preach the gospel to all <seg type="lb" n="11" />
					    creation.</seg>
					<seg n="16" type="verse">Whoever believes and is baptized will be <seg type="lb" n="12" /> saved, but whoever does not believe
					    will be condemned. <seg type="lb" n="13" /></seg>
					<seg n="17" type="verse">And these signs will accompany those who believe: <seg type="lb" n="14" /> In my name they will drive
					    out demons; they will <seg type="lb" n="15" /> speak in new tongues;</seg>
					<seg n="18" type="verse">they will pick up snakes with their hands; <seg type="lb" n="16" /> and when they drink deadly poison,
					    it will not hurt them at all; they will place their <seg type="lb" n="17" /> hands on sick people, and they will <seg type="lb" n="18" />
					    get well.”</seg>
				</p>	
				<p> 	
					<seg n="19" type="verse">After the Lord Jesus had spoken to them, <seg type="lb" n="19" /> he was taken up into heaven and he sat
					    <seg type="lb" n="20" /> <seg type="pb" n="108v" /> at the right hand of God.</seg>
					<seg n="20" type="verse">Then the disciples went out and preached <seg type="lb" n="1" /> everywhere, and the Lord worked with them
					    and confirmed his word by <seg type="lb" n="2" /> the signs that accompanied it.</seg>
				</p>	
                        </div>
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>		
		
